<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">
<channel>
    <title>Planet Neon Articles Feed</title>
    <link>https://neongod.neocities.org</link>
    <description>Latest articles on Planet Neon</description>
    <item>
        <title>AmigaNOS (KA9Q) TCP/IP configuration</title>
        <link>https://neongod.neocities.org/articles/a500-amiganos.html</link>
        <guid>https://neongod.neocities.org/articles/a500-amiganos.html</guid>
        <pubDate>Sun, 01 Dec 2024 21:39:32 GMT</pubDate>
        <description><![CDATA[    <div class="right-column column">
      <h2>TCP/IP through serial, between an Amiga 500 and Linux</h2>

      <p>AmigaNOS (or AmigaTCP or KA9Q) is as far as I know the only TCP/IP stack that works on Kickstart 1.3, besides Commodore's AS225 stack (and probably just it's r1 version), made for the <a href="https://bigbookofamigahardware.com/bboah/product.aspx?id=905" target="_blank">A2065</a> Zorro-II Ethernet card for Amiga 2000/3000/4000. By the time the Internet became more widespread, Kickstart 2.0 was already out and the more advanced applications all use the capabilities of the newer OS.</p>
      <p>AmigaNOS is the port of the TCP/IP stack originally written by Phil Karn (callsign: KA9Q) and was intended for amateur packet radio users. As it's tiny and was written in C, it got ported to many systems. The Amiga port was done by John Heaton.</p>

      <p>Even though there is an extensive original documentation. The Amiga version was maintained by different people over the years, so there are different archives in circulation with different features, folder structure (or the lack of it) and a confusing scattered documentation.</p>

      <h2>AmigaNOS versions</h2>
      <p><b>AmigaNOS v870227.5</b> - Archive: <a href="http://aminet.net/package/comm/tcp/AmigaTCP" target="_blank">AmigaTCP.lha</a> (AmiNet) -> Uploaded in 1989. An early version from the Fish collection. It lacks many features. No PPP support and the archive contains no documentation and folder structure for the configurations, but it includes the source code.</p>
      <p><b>AmigaNOS v2.9i</b> - Archive <a href="http://ftp.funet.fi/pub/amiga/datacomm/tcpip/AmigaNOS-2.9i.lha" target="_blank">AmigaNOS-2.9i.lha</a> (Funet FTP) -> The <b>full archive</b>, that contains the configuration files, folders and documentation, but this version has only SLIP support, so PPP won't work with it. I uploaded it to my cloud storage, so <a href="https://www.jottacloud.com/s/03095354bda6f10433aa30b01db0e3aee3c" target="_blank">here is a mirror</a>.</p>
      <p><b>AmigaNOS v2.9n</b> - Archive: <a href="http://aminet.net/package/comm/tcp/anos29m" target="_blank">anos29m.lha</a> (AmiNet) -> Uploaded in 1993, it's a newer version with SLIP and PPP support. It looks for the NOS-startup script in the AmigaNOS/tcpip/slip directory by default and if a NOS-dialup script is present, it will try to run that first (autodial is on). The archive contains just the executable, nothing else. Yes, the archive name says anos29m and the binary in it 2.9n, it's weird.</p>
      <p><b>AmigaNOS v2.9k</b> - Archive: <a href="http://aminet.net/package/comm/net/AmigaNOSGW6" target="_blank">AmigaNOSGW6.lzh</a> (AmiNet) -> It's the latest executable done by Graham Walter called AmigaNOSGW. It has SLIP and PPP, Van Jacobson IP header compression support and a partial BSD socket interface impelemtation via an Amiga message port, that allows the use of a Gopher client with AmigaGuide as a browser. It's based on AmigaNOS_v2.9n, but it looks for the NOS-startup script in the same directory where it runs by default. I'm using this version in this guide.</p>

      <p>There is an archive called <a href="http://aminet.net/package/comm/net/AmigaNOS-Tools" target="_blank">AmigaNOS-Tools.lha</a> (AmiNet) that contains some AREXX utilities targetted for radio amateur users.</p>


      <h2>AmigaNOS Complete</h2>

      <p>I made a "complete" AmigaNOS archive, which combines the different archives.</p>
      <ul><li>The folders from John Heaton's archive (AmigaNOS-2.9i.lha)</li>
        <li>Graham Walter's executable and Gopher client (from AmigaNOSGW6.lzh)</li>
        <li>The sources from the early AmigaTCP archive</li>
        <li>Contents of the AmigaNOS-Tools</li>
        <li>Workbench 1.3 compatible AmigaGuide and AmigaGuide.library has been included</li>
        <li>A Doc folder has been added, all the documentation found in the different archives moved there, and renamed to clean up things a bit</li>
        <li>Added an example NOS-Startup script with PPP and SLIP configuration</li>
        <li>Added icons for the main configuration files and the executable so it can be launched from Workbench</li>
        <li>In the AmigaNOS.guide I removed the "Commit suicide" text from the Troubleshooting section, as I found it offensive and I was not OK distributing that further</li>
        <li>Added an Installation.readme with the relevant parts of this guide</li></ul> 
      <p>You can download the complete archive here:</p>
      <p><a href="https://www.jottacloud.com/s/030bd8a4914b2a94e0c8cfbe3b3220a10ed" target="_blank">AmigaNOS-Complete.lha</a></p>


<br>
      <h1>AmigaNOS Installation</h1>

      <p>1. Download <a href="https://www.jottacloud.com/s/030bd8a4914b2a94e0c8cfbe3b3220a10ed" target="_blank">AmigaNOS-Complete.lha</a></p>
      <p>2. Unpack the archive to a location of your choice. For example your Workbench disk (sys:)</p>
      <p>3. Edit your s:startupII (or startup-sequence) script and add the following section:</p>
<pre>;Setup AmigaNOS
assign nos: sys:AmigaNOS
assign tcpip: nos:tcpip
assign slip: nos:tcpip/slip</pre>
      <p>4. Copy the files from AmigaNOS/c to your c: directory</p>
      <p>5. Copy the files from AmigaNOS/Libs to your libs: directory.</p>
      <p>6. Reboot, so the assigns are set</p>

      <p><i>Note: You can put the contents of the AmigaNOS-Complete archive on an empty floppy disk (excluding the documentation, the sources and AmigaGuide, so it fits on a single floppy) and use it on a floppy only system after booting from a Workbench 1.3 disk. Add the necessary assigns manually. Having two floppy drives is really recommended in this scenario.</i></p>

      <h2>Configure AmigaNOS PPP (Point-To-Point) connection</h2> 

      <p>Now you have AmigaNOS installed. The AmigaNOS/TCPIP directory contains a script called <b>NOS-startup</b>. The contents of this file gets executed when you start AmigaNOS (if you don't specify another directory where to look for the script with the -d argument ). You can also start AmigaNOS without a script, but then you'll need to enter the commands to configure the network connection manually every time.</p> 

      <p>Open the AmigaNOS/TCPIP/NOS-Startup script in a text editor and change the configuration according to your needs and your network. My script has the following settings:</p>
<pre>autodial off
ip address 10.0.0.2
hostname a500
attach asy serial.device 0 ppp ppp0 4096 1500 9600c  
route add default ppp0 10.0.0.1
domain addserver 10.0.0.1
start echo
start ping
#start telnet
#start ftp
#start ttylink
echo accept
ppp activeopen ppp0
ifconfig ppp0
ppp status ppp0
#domain trace on</pre>

    <p>In the first line we turn off autodial, so that the NOS-Dial script is not executed. We then set the IP address of the Amiga. I'm using 10.0.0.2 as the Amiga's address and 10.0.0.1 will be the RaspberryPi's PPP interface address. It's arbitrary, you can pick something else, just be consistent and use the same addresses on the Linux side. In theory you can even use unique IPs from the range of your main local network too (which is 192.168.10.x in my case), but it's a good idea to separate the two. The second line sets the hostname of the Amiga. The next important line is the attach, which configures the interface. AmigaNOS supports SLIP and PPP, I'm using PPP in this example. The command looks like this:<br>
    <pre>attach asy &lt;device&gt; &lt;unit&gt; &lt;mode&gt; &lt;if name&gt; &lt;buffer size&gt; &lt;MTU&gt; &lt;baud&gt;</pre>
    The values I set:<br>
    asy - it's always asy, don't ask why<br>
    serial.device - the device to use<br>
    0 - unit number of the device<br>
    ppp0 - my choice for the name for the ppp interface, it could be "nos" or anything else<br>
    4096 - buffer size<br>
    1500 - MTU (Max Trasmission Unit) size<br>
    9600 - baud rade<br>
    c - the last character after the baud rate sets RTS/CTS</p>
    <p>With "route add" command we add the IP address of the RaspberryPi as the default route for the ppp0 interface. We set DNS servers to the Raspberry Pi's ppp0 interface. Then we start some services. These are services that we provide from the Amiga, so they're the ones where the Amiga will act as a server and accept incoming packets. Then we activate the ppp connection and print the interface settings and the status of the connection. If you want to enable DNS traces, you can uncomment the last line.</p> 
    <p>Note: The ppp command has two modes: activeopen and passiveopen. Which one to use depends on how the pppd on the Linux side is configured (see the passive and silent parameters in the Linux pppd config file below).</p>

    <p>Open the AmigaNOS/TCPIP/domains.txt file in a text editor and replace the contents of it with the following line:</p>
<pre>&lt;hostname of your LinuxPC&gt; IN A 10.0.0.1</pre>
    <p>Note: There is an ftpusers file, which contains the username, password, path and permission for a user connecting to the Amiga's FTP server. You can configure it this way:</p>
<pre>&lt;user&gt; &lt;password&gt; &lt;directory&gt; &lt;permission&gt;</pre>
<p>Example:</p>
<pre>amiga amiga123 TCPIP:PUBLIC 1</pre>

    <h2>Configure PPPd  on Linux</h2>
    <p>It's time to configure the Linux side. I suggest following my <a href="a500-online-comprehensive-guide.html#amiga-pc-ppp">Amiga-PC PPP configuration</a> guide, where I set up the PPP connection between a RaspberryPi and a Workbench 3.1 running the Miami TCP/IP stack. For AmigaNOS however, we're going to need slightly different pppd settings, so set the following configuration in the /etc/ppp/amiga config file:</p>
<pre>debug
nodetach

# Serial device
/dev/ttyUSB0

# Speed of the serial line, this is probably maximum unless you have 
# a serial board (set the same as on the Amiga side!)
#2400
#19200
9600
#38400
#57600
#115200

# Require the peer to authenticate itself before allowing network
# packets to be sent or received.
noauth

# Don't use the modem control lines.
local

# Local and remote IP addresses
#192.168.10.201:192.168.10.202
10.0.0.1:10.0.0.2

# Set the interface netmask 
netmask 255.255.255.255

# Enables the "passive" option in the LCP.  With this option, pppd will
# attempt to initiate a connection; if no reply is received from the
# peer, pppd will then just wait passively for a valid LCP packet from
# the peer (instead of exiting, as it does without this option).
passive

# Add an entry to this system's ARP [Address Resolution Protocol]
# table with the IP address of the peer and the Ethernet address of this
# system.
proxyarp

# Do not exit after a connection is terminated; instead try to reopen
# the connection.
persist

# Disable Address/Control compression negotiation (use default, i.e.
# address/control field disabled).
-ac

# Disable protocol field compression negotiation (use default, i.e.
# protocol field compression disabled).
-pc

# Disable asyncmap negotiation (use the default asyncmap, i.e. escape
# all control characters).
#-am

# Disable negotiation of Van Jacobson style IP header compression (use
# default, i.e. no compression).
-vj

# Disable CCP compression and IPv6CP
nobsdcomp
noccp
noipv6</pre>

<p>As you can see, there is a slight difference compared to the guide for Miami, for AmigaNOS we're setting the baud rate to 9600, and disabling a bunch of compression negotiation. The rest of the <a href="a500-online-comprehensive-guide.html#amiga-pc-ppp">Amiga-PC PPP configuration</a> guide for the Raspberry Pi side to set up the IP forwarding and the pppd as a service pretty much still applies.</p>

<h2>Installing Dnsmasq</h2>
<p>This might not be strictly necessary as in theory DNS requests should also be forwarded if you enabled IP forwarding and set up the IP tables rules correctly, but for me for some reason while it worked well with Miami, it didn't work with AmigaNOS. I could see in tcpdump that the Amiga sent the DNS request to the Raspberry Pi, but it couldn't process it:</p>
<pre>18:00:53.311872 IP 10.0.0.2.1024 > 10.0.0.1.domain: 268+ A? www.google.com. (32)
18:00:53.312034 IP 10.0.0.1 > 10.0.0.2: ICMP 10.0.0.1 udp port domain unreachable, length 68</pre>

<p>The solution was to install Dnsmasq and force it to forward all DNS requests to the router. Here is how to do it.</p>
<p>Install Dnsmasq:</p>
<pre>sudo apt install dnsmasq</pre>
<p>Open it's configuration file:</p>
<pre>sudo nano /etc/dnsmasq.conf</pre>
<p>Add the following lines:</p>
<pre>interface=ppp0 
listen-address=10.0.0.1 # Raspberry Pi's address
server=192.168.10.1  # Forward DNS queries to your router
no-resolv  # Prevent dnsmasq from using /etc/resolv.conf</pre>

<p>Restart Dnsmasq</p>
<pre>sudo systemctl restart dnsmasq</pre>

<p>Once the ppp interface and dnsmasq is up and running on the Raspberry Pi, check the routing table, it should now contain a route for the ppp0 interface:</p>
<pre>route -n
Kernel IP routing table
Destination     Gateway         Genmask         Flags Metric Ref    Use Iface
0.0.0.0         192.168.10.1    0.0.0.0         UG    202    0        0 eth0
10.0.0.2        0.0.0.0         255.255.255.255 UH    0      0        0 ppp0
192.168.10.0    0.0.0.0         255.255.255.0   U     202    0        0 eth0</pre>

<p>We can now start AmigaNOS!</p>

<h2>Launching AmigaNOS</h2>
<p>To start AmigaNOS either click on the icon of the binary or start it from the CLI:</p>
<pre>cd tcpip:
amiganos</pre>
<p>An AmigaNOS commandline window will open and it should execute the settings from the nos-startup script, resulting in a ppp status command in the end. Wait a few seconds and type in the "ppp status ppp0" command again, to see if the connection is ready.
<p><i>Note: If you want to use a different startup script, you can specify a different folder for the script location with the -d argument. If the autodial parameter is set to ON, AmigaNOS will try to exectute the NOS-Dial script instead.</i></p>
<p>Now you should be able to use both FTP and Telnet towards the RaspberryPi's IP address. Type:</p> 
<pre>telnet 10.0.0.1</pre><p>or</p> 
<pre>ftp 10.0.0.1</pre>

<p><img src="../images/amiganos-2.jpg"></p>
<p><img src="../images/amiganos-3.jpg"></p>

<p>Try ping-ing an exteral domain name:</p>
<pre>ping google.com</pre>
<p><img src="../images/amiganos-4.jpg"></p>

<p>Connect to Aminet:</p>
<pre>ftp ftp.aminet.net</pre>
<p><img src="../images/amiganos-5.jpg"></p>

<h2>Some help in using the command-line</h2>
<p>By starting telnet or ftp, a new session window will open. You can have multiple sessions in AmigaNOS. To go back to the command-line window press the Clrl + ^ key. It will switch back to the command-line window, where you can start another session, or list and manage the running sessions with the session (or "se" for short) command. To stop an FTP session for example you can use:</p>
<pre>abort &lt;session #&gt;</pre>
<p>To see what commands are available, type:</p>
<pre>?</pre>
<p>For help on a particular command, type the command name before the "?". Example:</p>
<pre>domain ?</pre>
<p>For even more help, use the help &lt;command&gt;. Example:</p>
<pre>help domain</pre>
<p>This will open the relevant section for that command from the documentation. See the full documentation for more details.</p>
<p>To exit a running Telnet session, type "exit" in the Telnet terminal. To quit the FTP client, type "quit" in the FTP window. To stop AmigaNOS, type "exit" in the command-line window.</p>

<h2>Gopher and AmigaGuide</h2>
<p>Graham Walter's AmigaNOS (AmigaNOSGW6, v2.9k) has been extended with the possibility to run a Gopher client and use AmigaGuide as a "browser". If you have AmigaGuide installed (you copied the amigaguide binary from AmigaNOS:C to C: and AmigaNOS:Libs to Libs:), you can issue the command from the AmigaNOS commandline:</p>
<pre>client gopher</pre>
<p>The Gopher client will start and open a new window with AmigaGuide.</p>

<p><img src="../images/amiganos-6.jpg"></p>

<p>Click the Enter Gopher World button and select an address from the list. The list is stored in the tcpip:spool/gopher/bookmarks file. You can edit it to add new addresses or replace old, broken ones.</p>

<p><img src="../images/amiganos-7.jpg"></p>

<p>Enjoy browsing the Gopherspace on your Amiga 500!</p>
<p><img src="../images/amiganos-8.jpg"></p>

<br><br>

<h1>Alternative way</h2>

<h2>Configure AmigaNOS SLIP connection</h2> 

<p>Even though SLIP was pretty much replaced by PPP for direct point-to-point connections, it's possible to use SLIP as well.</p>
<p>In the AmigaNOS NOS-startup script you have to change just a few things. Specify slip in the attach command, change the interface name to sl0 and the MTU size to 576, remove the letter c from end of the baud value. Update the ppp0 interface name in the route commands with sl0, then remove the last two ppp commands. The changed commands:</p>
<pre>
attach asy serial.device 0 slip sl0 4096 576 9600  
route add 10.0.0.1 sl0
route default sl0 10.0.0.1
</pre>

<h2>Configure SLIP on RaspberryPi/Linux</h2>
<p>First, bring down the ppp0 interface if you configured it before:</p>
<pre>sudo systemctl stop ppp-amiga</pre>
<p>Then enable SLIP with:</p>
<pre>sudo modprobe slip</pre>
<p>Now you can configure it with:</p>
<pre>sudo slattach -v -d -p slip -s 9600 /dev/ttyUSB0 &</pre>
<p>Where 9600 is the baud rate and /dev/ttyUSB0 is the serial device in case you're using a USB-To-Serial adapter.</p>
<p>Running the command should give the following output:</p>
<pre>slattach: tty_open: looking for lock
slattach: tty_open: trying to open /dev/ttyUSB0
slattach: tty_open: /dev/ttyUSB0 (fd=3)
slattach: tty_set_speed: 9600
slattach: tty_set_databits: 8
slattach: tty_set_stopbits: 1
slattach: tty_set_parity: N
slip started on /dev/ttyUSB0 interface sl0</pre>
<p>Now we can configure the IP addresses for the sl0 interface and bring it up:</p>
<pre>sudo ifconfig sl0 10.0.0.1 pointopoint 10.0.0.2 up</pre>
<p>Set the MTU value to match what we configured in AmigaNOS:</p>
<pre>sudo ifconfig sl0 mtu 576</pre>
<p>What's left to do now is to configure the forwarding between the wlan0 (wifi) interface and the sl0 (slip) interface:</p>
<pre>sudo iptables -A FORWARD -o wlan0 -i sl0 -s 10.0.0.0/24 -m conntrack --ctstate NEW -j ACCEPT 
sudo iptables -A FORWARD -m conntrack --ctstate ESTABLISHED,RELATED -j ACCEPT 
sudo iptables -A POSTROUTING -t nat -j MASQUERADE</pre>]]></description>
    </item>
    <item>
        <title>Transfer files between PC/Mac and Amiga with a GOTEK drive</title>
        <link>https://neongod.neocities.org/articles/a500-gotek-file-transfer.html</link>
        <guid>https://neongod.neocities.org/articles/a500-gotek-file-transfer.html</guid>
        <pubDate>Thu, 05 Dec 2024 13:27:16 GMT</pubDate>
        <description><![CDATA[    <div class="right-column column">
    <p>There are plenty of ways to transfer files between a modern computer and your Amiga 500. Some are very slow (serial cable), others are expensive (modern expansions on the CPU slot). There is an SDbox hardware that connects to the parallel port, which might be a good solution, but I haven't tested it yet and I heard about issues (especially with Kickstart 1.3). What most people have nowadays however is a GOTEK floppy emulator. Either replacing the internal floppy drive or connected externally as a secondary floppy drive. Transferring ADF files are a breeze, you just copy them to your USB stick and that's it. But what if you'd want to try stuff that's on Aminet, the Fred Fish disks or somewhere else? They usually come lha compressed or in executables. How do you transfer those?</p>
    <h2>Prepare an emulator</h2>
    <p>I'm using <a href="https://fs-uae.net/" target="_blank">FS-UAE</a> under MacOS, but the principle is the same with WinUAE under Windows too.</p>
    <p>Open your emulator (FS-UAE Launcher) and have a Workbench floppy image at hand.</p>
    <p>Click the menu icon in the top left corner and open the ADF creator. Create two new standard ADF images. I named them filetransfer1.adf and filetransfer2.adf. Save them to a location that's easily accessible like that Desktop or find them in /Users/your-user/Documents/FS-UAE/Floppies</p>
    <p><img src="../images/fsuae1.gif"></p>
    <p><img src="../images/fsuae2.gif"></p>
    <p>Configure your emulator to emulate your Amiga 500. Amiga Model: A500, 1.3 ROM.</p> 
    <p>Floppy Drive: Insert the Workbench 1.3 disk to drive 0 (first drive) and the empty ADFs you created to drive 1 and 2 (second and third drive).</p>
   <p><img src="../images/fsuae3-0.gif"></p>
    <p>On the Hard Drives tab browse for a folder that will contain the stuff you downloaded and want to put on the new ADF. Can be your Downloads folder or create a separate Amiga folder for this.</p>
    <p><img src="../images/fsuae3-2.gif"></p>

    <p>On the ROM tab select your Kickstart 1.3 ROM file. Configure the RAM settings to match your machine (or more if you want).</p>
    <p><img src="../images/fsuae3-1.gif"></p>
    <p>Click on the menu icon in the top left corner again, then select the Settings option.</p>
    <p><img src="../images/fsuae4.gif"></p>
    <p>In the new window, click on Advanced and type in the following configuration lines:</p>
    <pre># Set the floppy drive speed to 8x
floppy_drive_speed = 800

# To allow changes to be written to ADF files
# Without this FS-UAE never saves to ADF files directly, it creates an overlay diff file instead 
writable_floppy_images = 1
</pre>
    <p><img src="../images/fsuae5.gif"></p>
    <p>Without the writeable_floppy_images=1 option FS-UAE will protect your ADFs and won't save your changes to the original file. It creates a Floppy overlay file in Documents/FS-UAE/Floppy Overlays for every disk instead. After adding this option it should work as you'd expect it to, and save your stuff properly.</p>
    <p>Close the advanced settings, give a name to your configuration instead of "Unnamed Configuration" and click the save config button next to it.</p>
    <p>Download the following stuff and place it in your shared folder (the one you configured in FS-UAE as an Amiga drive):</p>
    <ul>
        <li><a href="https://www.jottacloud.com/s/03037894ee19c1b4236aa7ce067df36c106" target="_blank">Lha v1.38 extractor</a> (This is a Kickstart 1.3 compatible version. The newer version on Aminet unfortunately doesn't work under Kickstart 1.3)</li>
        <li><a href="http://aminet.net/package/util/cli/splitter304a">Splitter304a</a> by Martin Schlodder (to split and join larger files to multiple floppies)</li>
    </ul>
    <p>Optional (but will make life much easier):</p>
    <ul>
        <li><a href="https://www.jottacloud.com/s/030450d588b95244b0fad9c4260748e9039" target="_blank">Disk Master 2.1</a> (the last version that works on older systems)</li>
    </ul>

    <p>You can add the Disk Master 2.1 ADF to the 4th floppy drive of the emulator.</p>
    <h2>Copy the files using the emulator</h2>
    <p>Start the emulator. After it booted, open the Workbench 1.3 disk and a new Shell. In the shell, type the following commands:</p>
    <pre>cd amiga:          // use your shared folder name
dir
lha                 // check that lha works
copy lha df1:       // copy the lha executable to your empty ADF</pre>
    <p><img src="../images/lha.gif"></p>

    <p>If you want, you can also drag the DM2 icon in Workbench from the Disk Master floppy to both your shared folder and the empty disk, so you'll always have a tool for copying and browsing files at hand.</p>
    <h2>Splitting bigger files</h2>
    <p>If you want to transfer bigger files that won't fit on a single floppy disk, you can use the Splitter tool. It can be used to split larger files into floppy disk sizes, then join them together on the Amiga side. This is only useful if you either have an extra memory expansion in your Amiga 500 (so you can extract and join files in RAM) or if you have a hard drive.</p>
    <p>Here is how to do it:</p>
    <pre>
lha x splitter304a.lha              // extract the splitter
rename splitter splitter304a        // rename the splitter folder to avoid conflict
copy splitter304/splitter amiga:    // copy the tool from it's folder to the shared volume 
copy splitter df1:                  // copy it to the filetransfer1.adf</pre>
    <p>Now let's try it on some larger file. I'm using the mui38usr.lha here as an example, which is a 1MB file:</p>
    <pre>
splitter -h                          // gives you detailed help
splitter mui38usr.lha                // will split the file to two 720kbyte chunks
splitter -s amiofsdc-dd muiusr38.lha // will split the file into two 840kbyte 
                                     // chunks (Amiga OFS Dir-Cache Double Density)</pre>
    <p><img src="../images/splitter1.gif"></p>
    <p>Joining the files is similarly easy. You just specify -j as join, then list the source files and in the end the destination file:</p>
    <pre>splitter -j muiusr38.lha.001 muiusr38.lha.002 muiusr38-joined.lha</pre>
    <p><img src="../images/splitter2.gif"></p>

    <p>After you copied the files to the filetransfer1 and filetransfer2 ADFs, you can quit the emulator, copy the ADFs to your GOTEK's USB stick and use them on your Amiga.</p>]]></description>
    </item>
    <item>
        <title>Connecting the Amiga 500 to an HDMI display</title>
        <link>https://neongod.neocities.org/articles/a500-hdmi-video.html</link>
        <guid>https://neongod.neocities.org/articles/a500-hdmi-video.html</guid>
        <pubDate>Fri, 06 Dec 2024 13:55:04 GMT</pubDate>
        <description><![CDATA[    <div class="right-column column">

      <p>I got the urge to connect my Amiga 500 to our living room TV, with the goal of playing games together with my
        family from the couch. The problem is however, that our flat screen TV is fairly new and has only HDMI inputs.
      </p>

      <p>Lack of connectivity is only part of the problem. Another issue is the supported resolutions. Most Amiga
        software uses either PAL/NTSC lowres or hires-interlaced resolutions and most modern TVs can't display these
        correctly, without conversion and processing. Even those that can handle 240p, often interpret it as 480i.</p>

      <p>The Amiga 500 has a Composite out RCA jack (called Mono), which outputs a Black & White signal, and a Video
        port with a DB23 connector with an RGB signal. There are a number of ways to turn these into something an HDMI
        TV (or monitor) can handle, but most boil down to two things:<br>
        1. An upscaler/HDMI converter device<br>
        2. A way of making the connection between the upscaler and the Amiga, so some sort of cable or adaptor+cable</p>

      <p>There are also a number of aspects to consider, including picture quality, latency and of course cost. In
        general we can say that the quality of the analog video standards goes like this: Component and RGB is the best,
        S-Video is good, Composite is fine on CRTs, but poor on flat screens and RF is the worst with lots of
        interference in today's electrically crowded world. Regarding latency, cheap Chinese upscalers (found on Amazon
        and eBay) will add significantly more lag than the more expensive and quality upscalers made with retro gaming
        in mind. Does that mean that a cheaper solution is necessarily bad and should be avoided? No, just know your
        needs as you'll get what you pay for.</p>

      <p>The three biggest names in the retro-gaming scene are RetroTINK, OSSC and Framemeister. I'm dismissing the
        latter here due to it's inavailability, high price and the fact that the OSSC pretty much made it obsolete, and
        will focus on the first two and some other less known options.</p>
      <p>The <a href="https://www.retrotink.com/">RetroTINK</a> is made by Mike Chi and it's based on his proprietary
        design and firmware. There is a Chinese clone on the market called RetroScaler2X, which is a ripoff of the first
        RetroTINK 2X (not the Pro), before the firmware was encrypted. Even though it's cheaper than the original, I
        would advice against supporting this way of making business. I'm also excluding the previous official RetroTINK
        products like the SCART and Mini, which are out of stock due to supply shortage and will probably be
        discontinued, so you can only buy them on the second hand market.</p>

      <p>The OSSC stands for Open Source Scan Converter, which is an open source design and several companies make
        assembled end-user products from it, including <a
          href="https://videogameperfection.com/products/open-source-scan-converter/">VideoGamePerfection</a>, <a
          href="https://www.amazon.com/dp/B083FG6PXH/ref=cm_sw_r_cp_api_glt_fabc_665ZKD1AHE1WFRZS31CC">Mcbazel</a>, <a
          href="https://kaicolabs.com/product/kaico-edition-open-source-scan-converter-ossc/">Keico</a> and <a
          href="https://www.bitfunx.com/product/bitfunx-ossc-open-source-scan-converter-hdmi-adapter-for-retro-game-consoles-ps2-sega-saturn-nintendo-64-pc-engine/">Bitfunx</a>.
        VideoGamePerfection is the "definitive" one, which uses the latest design and updates, the others being a bit
        behind (and sometimes being cheaper). Mcbazel (among other manufacturers) also makes an upscaler called <a
          href="https://www.amazon.se/Mcbazel-ODV-GBS-C-Component-Console-st%C3%B6d-1080p-utg%C3%A5ng/dp/B0B3XPJCDZ">ODV-GBS-C</a>,
        which is based on the open source project of <a
          href="the https://github.com/ramapcsx2/gbs-control">GBS-Control</a>. It's an updated and enhanced design of
        the Tvia Trueview5725 based upscalers used in arcade machines, with more connectivity options and a new custom
        Firmware.</p>

      <h2>Let's see the options</h2>

      <p><b>Note:</b> The indicated price ranges are just approximate and at the time of writing this. VAT, customs and
        shipping can affect them significantly based on your location.</p>

      <h3>Composite</h3>

      <p><b>A520 TV modulator + AV2HDMI adapter</b><br>
        The original Commodore TV modulator creates an RF and a Composite output. Most modern TVs still have an
        RF/antenna input, but it's most probably not even worth to try. The composite signal can be converted to HDMI
        with a cheap AV2HDMI adaptor from Amazon like <a
          href="https://www.amazon.co.uk/AV2HDMI-Adapter-Composite-Converter-Support-White/dp/B0791YSS5Q/ref=sr_1_1_sspa?crid=2DXK5ONORFMMR&keywords=av2hdmi&qid=1700040502&s=electronics&sprefix=av2hdm%2Celectronics%2C180&sr=1-1-spons&sp_csd=d2lkZ2V0TmFtZT1zcF9hdGY&psc=1">this
          one</a>.<br>
        If you already have an A520 TV modulator, this is the cheapest solution. But will result in the worst possible
        picture quality, where the text is barely readable and as these adaptors were made with VHS/DVD in mind, they
        also have a pretty significant lag, which can be annoying in games where precision is required.<br>
        <b>Note:</b> It's possible to modify the A520 modulator to output an S-Video signal, see below.<br>
        <b>Price range:</b> 10 USD (and an additional 20-30 USD if you need to buy a used A520)</b>
      </p>

      <p><img src="../images/av2hdmi.jpg"></p>

      <h3>S-Video</h3>

      <p><b>RGB to S-Video adapter + S-Video input on an upscaler (RetroTINK 2x-Pro)</b><br>
        The <a href="https://www.retrotink.com/product-page/retrotink-2x-pro">RetroTINK 2x-Pro</a> is an upscaler made
        with retro gaming in mind. It works out of the box and doesn't require configuration. It has Composite,
        Component and S-Video inputs. With S-Video we can get a decent quality output and there are several ways to get
        this signal out of the Amiga 500. We can either <a
          href="https://zenithsal.com/amiga/2018/06/01/amiga-a500-a520-s-video-mod">mod an existing A520 TV
          modulator</a>, build our own S-Video adapter based on <a
          href="https://retrohax.net/rgb4all-composite-and-s-video-module/">this</a> or <a
          href="https://www.everythingamiga.com/2017/02/amiga-rgb-to-s-video-adapter.html">this</a> guide, or buy a
        ready-made internal module <a
          href="https://www.retropassion.co.uk/product/amiga-a500-composite-s-video/">here</a> or <a
          href="https://www.ebay.co.uk/itm/323934490842?_trkparms=amclksrc%3DITM%26aid%3D1110025%26algo%3DHOMESPLICE.COMPOSITELISTINGS%26ao%3D1%26asc%3D256560%26meid%3D80dda1793501492685aa8c93f7656360%26pid%3D101506%26rk%3D9%26rkt%3D25%26sd%3D266124515352%26itm%3D323934490842%26pmt%3D0%26noa%3D1%26pg%3D3458402%26algv%3DAlgoIndex5SimRanker%26brand%3DMarkenlos&_trksid=p3458402.c101506.m1851">here</a>.
        The solution with the S-Video and Composite output module however, requires some soldering and a hole drilled in
        the Amiga 500's case.</p>

      <p><img src="../images/retrotink.jpg"></p>

      <p>Another option is a ready-made adapter cable called <b>Amiga Excalibur</b> <a
          href="https://www.ebay.co.uk/itm/266124515352">here</a> or <a
          href="https://www.tindie.com/products/axel81l/amiga-svideo-cvbs-video-converter-pal-ntsc-new/">here</a>, which
        has the adapter built into it's DB23 connector. This cable comes in different variations, there is a 2-in-1
        version too, that will give you both an S-Video and Composite output. There are different cables for PAL or NTSC
        TVs, so you need to pick one for your system.<br>
        <b>Price Range:</b> 180 USD (cable 40, RetroTINK 2x-Pro 140)
      </p>

      <p><img src="../images/amiga-excalibur-s-video.jpg"></p>

      <h3>RGB-SCART</h3>

      <p><b>RGB-SCART cable + a cheap SCART/RGB to HDMI converter</b><br>
        A cost effective solution with a decent picture quality as it's using the RGB signal, but expect some added lag
        by the cheap converter. It's not perfect for gaming where timing is critical, but if you want to connect only
        your Amiga (or other systems with an RGB output), this is probably the most simple and best value for money
        solution you can find.<br>
        You can make your own SCART cable based on <a href="http://www.ianstedman.co.uk/amiga-scart-guide">this
          guide</a> or buy a <a
          href="https://www.amiga-shop.net/en/Amiga-Hardware/Amiga-cables-adapters/Amiga-RGB-cable-original-DB23-to-SCART::757.html">ready-made
          cable</a>.<br>
        <b>Note 1:</b> Some online stores sell cables with a modified DB25 connector, the one above uses an original
        DB23 connector.<br>
        <b>Note 2:</b> A SCART connector can be used to transmit either a Composite or an RGB signal. There are many
        SCART to HDMI converters out there, but not all of them work with an RGB signal. <a
          href="https://www.amazon.co.uk/gp/product/B078JJMR5J/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&psc=1&linkCode=sl1&tag=kdyson-21&linkId=32a0d91326576ec959c6635b82d1a180&language=en_GB">Here
          is one</a> that should work.<br>
        <b>Price Range:</b> 55 USD (cable 25, converter 30)
      </p>

      <p><img src="../images/scart2hdmi.jpg"></p>

      <p><b>RGB-SCART cable + a quality upscaler (OSSC, ODV-GBS-C, RetroTINK 5X-Pro)</b><br>
        A nicer and better quality solution with no lag, but a higher price tag. The <a
          href="ttps://videogameperfection.com/products/open-source-scan-converter/?sld=retrorgb">OSSC</a> is a flexible
        and extendable upscaler with an RGB/SCART and Component input and an upgradable firmware. It's also rather
        complicated, with a wast amount of settings to play around with. But if you dig into it, you can surely find the
        best present and options to make it look perfect on practically any screen and there are frequent updates to
        it's firmware and features. It struggles however when switching resolutions due to it's design (preventing the
        signal drop would require a frame rate conversion, which needs more buffer memory than the OSSC has). It takes a
        few seconds to switch, which can be annoying if it happens during gameplay or a demo. Some Amiga games also
        switch resolutions when displaying high-res title and loading screens, but it's even more annoying if you have
        other retro systems too like the PS2, where it was common for developers to use 240p for the game and 480i for
        the in-game menus.</p>

      <p><img src="../images/ossc.jpg"></p>

      <p>The <a href="https://www.odv-gbsc.com/products/odv-gbs-c-converter-for-retro-gaming-console">ODV-GBS-C</a> is
        an upscaler specially designed for classic retro game consoles. It's based on a generic upscaler for arcade
        machines, with many improvements. It converts YPbPr component and RGB signals to HDMI and VGA. It's also lag
        free and supports dynamic de-interlacing, scanline effect and no delay for 240p/480i switching (unlike the
        OSSC). It can even downscale higher resolution inputs to 240p, for displaying them on a CRT. Mcbazel's model can
        be found on <a
          href="https://www.amazon.com/Mcbazel-ODV-GBS-C-Component-Converter-Console/dp/B0B4B2CM9F/ref=sr_1_1_sspa?crid=2AVUH822VIN7F&keywords=Mcbazel+ODV-GBS-C&qid=1700662045&sprefix=mcbazel+odv-gbs-c%2Caps%2C321&sr=8-1-spons&sp_csd=d2lkZ2V0TmFtZT1zcF9hdGY&psc=1">Amazon</a>.
        If quick resolution switching and dynamic de-interlacing is an important factor for you, I recommend looking at
        this option, it's also significantly cheaper than OSSC.</br>
        <b>Note:</b> As GBS-Control is an open-source project, you can also build a scaler on your own. There are even
        <a href="https://www.retroupgrades.co.uk/product/gbs-c-aio/">All-In-One kits</a> available, which make this the
        cheapest quality solution for people who like soldering.
      </p>

      <p><img src="../images/gbsc.jpg"></p>

      <p>The <a href="https://www.retrotink.com/product-page/5x-pro">RetroTINK 5x-Pro</a> is considered to be the top of
        the class by many in the retro gaming scene, and it's price is reflecting that. Currently sold at 325 USD makes
        it the most expensive option. If you're in Europe, with the tax and shipping it will be closer to 400. For this
        price however you get an FPGA based upscaler, a hassle-free plug and play solution that works with virtually
        every possible analog input and can upscale to 1080p (as opposed the RetroTINK 2X models that can only double to
        480p).<br>
        <b>Price Range:</b> 115-350 USD (cable 25, OSSC 150, ODV-GBS-C 90, RetroTINK 5X-Pro 325)
      </p>

      <p><img src="../images/retrotink5xpro.jpg"></p>

      <h3>Component</h3>

      <p><b>RGB to Component adapter + Component input on an upscaler (OSSC, ODV-CBS-C, RetroTINK 2X-Pro,
          5X-Pro)</b><br>
        You can convert the Amiga's RGB output to Component with an external adapter, and use practially any quality
        upscaler with it.<br>
        The signal on the Mono output it basically the Luma of the Component video, with CSYNC. It's possible to use the
        Luma signal from the Mono jack and combine it with Pb and Pr signals we can get from the RGB port. There is no
        ready made solution for this, but you can make your own adapter based on <a
          href="https://github.com/c0pperdragon/AmigaYPbPrAdapter">this guide</a>.</p>
      <p>Another way is to use only the RGB port to generate a Component output, you can build your own adapter based on
        <a href="https://gglabs.us/node/983">this project</a>, or you can buy this nice and reasonably priced pre-built
        adapter from a RetronicDesign, a Canadian manufacturer: <a
          href="https://www.tindie.com/products/retronicdesign/commodore-amiga-video-to-components-adapter">here</a> or
        <a
          href="https://www.ebay.com/itm/185866422419?hash=item2b46808893:g:hPcAAOSwl8xkRGF3&amdata=enc%3AAQAIAAAA4OaBBL7RlZW304xTVvGIGZqu10%2B5ABUAo4ueg1mBGDo4TAj21%2BLGulxIk%2BwmR0cJ5%2BXxZ06kn2UGJmFy6xVlglKENiTD2jxfKu7hsoiHHkiNTU%2BPZTsNTfIgI%2BnJJw62XoU1bDE3G6Ho5Gqu2JJrY9cqm5h%2BbvrqdxTb5rYAdadQFwX1Jc1n1M1B9XjC%2Bg1yEOqqeGBFge3fWguffRW4OfPBA8UcT840emgBFCbAoWNWUObbqP1yeXPL4aC5qferi9jNrpebldo6OXPw0QWnm3kn%2FtSphDndWfGL8dxJpPgu%7Ctkp%3ABk9SR_jZwbf6Yg">here</a>.<br>
        <b>Price Range:</b> 180-400 USD (component adapter 40-50, RetroTINK/OSSC 140-150, ODV-GBS-C 90, RetroTINK 5X-Pro
        325)
      </p>

      <p><img src="../images/amiga-to-component.jpg"></p>

      <h3>Direct HDMI output</h3>

      <p><b>HDMI output with an internal Pi Zero adapter</b><br>
        This is an internal mod, adding an adapter to the Denise chip to hijack the video signal and convert it to HDMI
        with a Pi Zero. Buy the adapter <a
          href="https://www.retroguru.eu/product/amiga-rgbtohdmi-adapter-rgb-to-hdmi-raspberry-pi-zero/">here</a> or
        another version <a href="https://www.retropassion.co.uk/product/rgb2hdmi_amiga_500/">here</a>.<br>
        <b>Note:</b> You'll need to add a Pi Zero and an SD card with the appropriate software. Also, you have to ditch
        the internal shielding for it to fit, and find a way to lead the cable out of the case, maybe through the side
        expansion port (if you don't use it for something else). There is even an <a
          href="https://www.retro32.com/product/amiga-500-expansion-port-cover-for-rgb-to-hdmi-equipped-amiga-cable-access-hole">expansion
          port cover</a> with a cable access hole.<br>
        <b>Price Range:</b> 85 USD (adapter 40-50, Pi Zero 30, cover 10)
      </p>

      <p><img src="../images/rgb2hdmi-pi.jpg"></p>]]></description>
    </item>
    <item>
        <title>Bringing the Amiga 500 online, the comprehensive guide</title>
        <link>https://neongod.neocities.org/articles/a500-online-comprehensive-guide.html</link>
        <guid>https://neongod.neocities.org/articles/a500-online-comprehensive-guide.html</guid>
        <pubDate>Fri, 06 Dec 2024 13:45:45 GMT</pubDate>
        <description><![CDATA[    <div class="right-column column">

      <p>That's a bold title. There are obviously many ways to bring our beloved Amiga 500 online and I can't possibly
        cover them all in one article. What I will focus on here are the options avaialble with as stock setup of an
        Amiga 500 as possible.</p>
      <p>Before going any further, we need to clarify what do we exactly mean by online?
        Is it online like it was back in 1987 when the Amiga 500 was released or is it online like the <a
          href="#internettoday">Internet we know
          today</a>? Let's investigate both scenarios in a bit more detail.</p>

      <h2>1. Back in the day</h2>
      <p>Online meant dialing in to another computer through a <a
          href="https://toobnix.org/w/p4ZYu6LUhZXQpP7svcGVy2">modem</a> and a telephone line. Often that other machine
        was running a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bulletin_board_system">Bulletin Board System (BBS)</a>. Can
        we still do this today? In a way, yes, and I would like to argue that this is the most viable option for stock
        Amiga 500 owners.</p>

      <h3>What can this be used for?</h3>
      <p>Many fun things actually. There are old BBS servers that are online again on the telnet protocol and there are
        new ones too. There are various servers on telnet that provide fun and excitement for us geeks:</p>

      <ul>
        <li><b>telehack.com:23</b> for example lets you play the classic NetHack game, among many other things. You can
          even watch Star Wars Episode IV in the terminal!</li>
        <li>You can play chess on <b>freechess.org:5000</b> or Go on <b>igs.joyjoy.net:6969</b></li>
        <li>Or a Star Trek themed game on <b>mtrek.com:1701</b></li>
        <li>Gaming Museum on <b>gt.gamingmuseum.com:23</b> hosts a number of old BBS games ready to play</li>
        <li>There are numerous servers that provide text based adventure games, MUDs (Multi User Dungeon) RPG games and
          MUCKs (Multi-User Chat Kingdom) text-based role-playing games designed for social interaction. You can find a
          more comprehensive list of available servers <a
            href="https://store.chipkin.com/articles/telnet-list-of-telnet-servers">here</a> and <a
            href="http://www.mewbies.com/acute_terminal_fun_telnet_public_servers_watch_star_wars_play_games_etc.htm">here</a>.
        </li>
        <li>But most importantly, check the largest list of available BBS servers on <a
            href="https://www.telnetbbsguide.com/bbs/">TelnetBBSguide.com</a>, many updated daily, have a file download
          section and an active community.</li>
      </ul>

      <p><img src="../images/atalkIII-starwars.gif"></p>

      <p>If you have an own server in your local network, you can connect to it via telnet and use command line internet
        tools there.</p>

      <p>There are so called BBS doors, which are applications that provide a connection to other machines from the
        server running the
        BBS. Nowadays there are some that offer doors to the outside Internet, so it's possible to run a
        text based web browser, IRC or email client from the terminal there. One of such is the <a
          href="https://www.telnetbbsguide.com/bbs/public-electronic-networked-information-system/">
          Public Electronic Networked Information System</a>, which despite the horrible name, works pretty well and
        provides Usenet, Gopher, IRC and WWW access. It's neither safe nor nice, but it's possible to access the
        Internet this way on very low end machines, read the news, check the weather.</p>

      <p><img src="../images/atalkIII-startrek.gif"></p>


      <h3>How to connect?</h3>

      <p>There are several ways, but they can be practically distilled into two options:</p>
      <ol>
        <li>Connecting the Amiga 500 to a PC via a null modem cable and use a software on the PC side to emulate a
          modem, so we can dial in to a BBS through the Internet via Telnet. AmigaLove made a <a
            href="https://www.amigalove.com/viewtopic.php?f=5&t=168&sid=8745c76444d5e4e7138031eeaf3ffd94">very detailed
            guide on this</a>.</li>
        <li>Do the same thing with a hardware solution like a <a
            href="https://www.cbmstuff.com/index.php?route=product/product&product_id=59">WiModem232</a>. It emulates a
          Hayes compatible modem and can connect directly to your WiFi network.</li>
      </ol>

      <p>I would really recommend going with the second option as even though it's a bit more expensive, it will result
        in
        a much sealmess and nice experience, closer to how it originally was, without the need of poking around with a
        PC (which has to be next to your Amiga and turned on). As I have such a modem, I'd like to elaborate a bit more
        on how to set it up.</p>

      <h3 id="wimodem232-setup">Setup the WiModem232</h3>
      <p>If you've never done this before, no need to panic, it's pretty simple and straight forward. There is also good
        <a href="https://www.cbmstuff.com/downloads/wimodem/wimodem232_manual.pdf">documentation</a> on the modem and
        how to set it up.
      </p>
      <p>First, you need to plug the modem into the serial port of your Amiga and connect a 5V USB power source to it.
        Most mobile chargers would do.</p>
      <p>Then you'll need a terminal software, I recommend A-Talk III, as it runs well from floppy, very simple to setup
        and what's even better, Marco Papa of Felsina Software made it public domain in 2010. You can grab the <a
          href="https://www.jottacloud.com/s/0301eaa97b634a046b7ac18b1ba87e960fb">A-Talk III ADF here</a>, and <a
          href="https://www.jottacloud.com/s/0309496d08206f8468da07093c6b189443e">the manual here</a>. Just boot a
        Workbench 1.3 floppy up, insert the A-Talk III disk and launch it.</p>

      <p><img src="../images/atalkIII.gif"></p>
      <p>The Wimodem232 by default starts in a 300 baud mode, so you'll need to set your terminal to match that. Check
        the rest of the settings in the menu to match the following:<br>
        Parity - None<br>
        Stop Bits - 1<br>
        No. Bits - 8<br>
        Handshake - RTS/CTS<br>
        Duplex - Full</p>

      <p><img src="../images/atalkIII-setup.gif"></p>

      <p>Save your settings in the Project menu.</p>

      <p>By typing the command "ati", you can check the status information of the modem:</p>

      <p><img src="../images/wimodem232-1.gif"></p>

      <p>You can set the speed to faster (baud 9600) with:</p>
      <pre>AT*B9600</pre>
      <p>Then update your terminal's baud settings to match that.</p>
      <p>You can save the default configuration of the modem with:</p>
      <pre>AT&W</pre>
      <p>So it doesn't get lost in case you reboot or unplug the WiModem232. If you'd ever want to go back to factory
        defaults, you can issue the command:</p>
      <pre>AT&F</pre>
      <p>This won't clear your address book, but it will reset everything else, and set the baud rate back to 300. There
        are also two emergency reset pads on the bottom side of the modem, so if anything would go wrong, which is
        unlikely, you can reset the modem by shorting those pads while turning the modem on.</p>
      <p>It's time to configure the connection to your WIFI router. There are several ways to do this. The modem can
        serve you a web interface where you can configure the WIFI network from your phone or tablet. To enable this
        mode, type:</p>
      <pre>AT*WIFI</pre>
      <p>Now look at your mobile device and check the WIFI list. An entry called WiModem232 should appear. Click on that
        and you can configure the modem.</p>
      <p>Another way is to do it manually from the terminal directly. Issuing the following command will list all the
        available WIFI networks:</p>
      <pre>AT*N</pre>
      <p>Then you can select the one you'd like to connect to with the following command:</p>
      <pre>AT*NS&lt;number from the list&gt;,&lt;password&gt;

Example:
AT*NS1,Password123
    </pre>
      <p>Or, you can also set your router's SSID directly, with the following command:</p>
      <pre>AT*SSID&lt;your SSID&gt;,&lt;password&gt;

Example:
AT*SSIDMYROUTER,Password123
Note: There is no space between the letters "SSID" and the router's actual SSID.</pre>
      <p>Now you're connected!</p>
      <p>You can test if your connection works by connecting a server:</p>
      <pre>ATDT &lt;server domain or ip&gt;:&lt;port number&gt;

Example:
ATDT google.com:80</pre>
      <p>You should see "CONNECTED" on the screen. To hang up the connection, press the + key 3 times in a row very
        quickly, it should respond with saying "OK". Then you can type the command to hang up the connection:</p>
      <pre>ATH</pre>

      <p>You can also update the firmware of the modem now, it will reboot the modem, but your settings will be kept:
      </p>
      <pre>AT*UPDATE</pre>

      <p>And that's all there is to it really! You can connect to various BBS servers now, just pick your favourite.</p>

      <p><img src="../images/atalkIII-bbs.gif"></p>

      <h2 id="internettoday">2. Today's Internet</h2>

      <p>If by Online we mean accessing the actual Internet with applications running on our machine locally, that's a
        much more
        complicated problem and we have to awknowledge the limitations of the machine.</p>

      <p>The TCP/IP stack and all the client applications take up too much space and memory to be used from a floppy
        disk and with 1MB of RAM. Another issue is the Kickstart 1.3. When the Internet started to become more
        widespread in the 90s,
        Kickstart 2.0 was already out and most Amiga developers used its features for making network enabled OS-friendly
        applications.
        Therefore all of the more advanced TCP/IP stacks on Amiga require at least Kickstart 2.0.</p>
      <p>Besides Commodore's AS225 TCP/IP stack that came with the A2065 Zorro-II card for the Amiga 2000/3000/4000, the
        only TCP/IP stack that I'm aware of that runs on Kickstart 1.3 is <a
          href="https://theory.cs.uni-bonn.de/ppp/part5.html#amigappp">AmigaNOS (Network
          Operating System)</a>. It is a port of <a href="http://www.ka9q.net/code/ka9qnos/">KA9Q's NOS</a>, a TCP/IP
        stack made for amateur packet radio systems. It should work on an Amiga 500 with 1Mb RAM and two floppy drives
        (to skip frequent disk swapping), it supports SLIP/PPP, but none of the more "modern" internet applications will
        work with it, as it doesn't have a complete bsdsocket.library emulation.</p>
      <p>It has it's own
        command-line interface and you can use a few command-line applications like telnet, ftp, smtp, pop3 there. There
        isn't much documentation on it online, I only found <a
          href="http://web.tiscalinet.it/iw2fer/a500_nosconf_eng.htm">this one page</a>, which configures it for data
        exchange between an Amiga and a C64, so I decided to figure it out myself. I managed to set it up and can use
        the
        FTP client to transfer files or even browse the Gopherspace with a Gopher client that's using AmigaGuide. If
        you're interested how to configure it,
        see my <a href="a500-amiganos.html">AmigaNOS guide here</a>.</p>

      <p>I'm pretty sure however that it's not what most people mean when they say they'd like to bring their Amiga 500
        online.</p>

      <p>So what's the <b>bare minimum</b> needed to be able to use the graphical Internet applications (or at least
        some of
        them), from an Amiga 500?</p>

      <p>You could have guessed it already:<br>Kickstart 2.0+, some extra memory and realistically, a hard drive.</p>

      <p>If you don't have a hard drive, you can try TermiteTCP, which runs from a single floppy. I prepared a disk for
        you, <a href="#termitetcp">see below</a>. But to run some applications along it like a web browser, you'll need
        more memory and a hard drive.</p>

      <p>My choice was a <a href="https://bigbookofamigahardware.com/bboah/product.aspx?id=534">Commodore A590</a>,
        which was the official hard drive offering from Commodore for the Amiga 500.
        It's a SCSI controller with a maximum of 2MB extra memory expansion inside. There were other manufacturers who
        offered hard drives too, like AlfaData/BSC with their <a
          href="https://bigbookofamigahardware.com/bboah/product.aspx?id=522">AlfaPower 500</a>
        and GVP with the <a href="https://bigbookofamigahardware.com/bboah/product.aspx?id=1784">A500 HD+</a>. Today we
        also have the option
        to buy a new expansion board that has everything included, like an <a
          href="https://icomp.de/shop-icomp/en/shop/product/ACA500plus.html">ACA500+</a> with a <a
          href="https://icomp.de/shop-icomp/en/produkt-details/product/x-surf-500.html#filter=*">X-Surf 500</a> network
        card. But for me the
        appeal in all this was the challenge to make it work with original and authentic hardware, and find the most
        basic and authentic setup possible,
        so this guide tries to cover that scenario.</p>

      <p>The obvious question pops up, if we can use the <a
          href="https://www.cbmstuff.com/forum/showthread.php?tid=440">WiModem232 with a TCP/IP stack</a>. In theory, it
        should work with a PPP/SLIP connection, but in practice, I don't know of anyone who managed to make it work,
        including myself. If you do know someone, let me know!</p>

      <p>Before tackling the challenge on bringing the system online, we need to solve two things:</p>
      <ol>
        <li>Transfering files to the Amiga</li>
        <li>Having a Kickstart 2.0+</li>
      </ol>

      <p>There are several options for both. But without an expansion board, your options are limited to either
        transfering
        files with the help of <a href="https://www.amigaforever.com/ae/">AmigaExplorer</a> via a null modem cable (<a
          href="https://www.ebay.co.uk/itm/361535182471?hash=item542d2d1687:g:vHwAAOSwPc9WvI1U&amdata=enc%3AAQAIAAAA4DmH8PsioZg52l1kjzN2MLM0wVv%2BQx8qOA0wr%2Bi6L%2BCEicN9jkMJjUD9WsB%2F6jt63ns26oHbjMBD33xTtAHdYdN8kSIjHR2ySfkU3TItJGgQHDjD6%2BAFej1QaGlsG6B%2F%2Fd90AC2vSUDJkSkt%2B%2FI30GjFfZEgnD0Q5aHUg%2BP%2BIoRNaIj%2BbE34Yh9zIjbv%2BrQEPUwdVls540xrOIMprI8FzSqMVkFms0294y1i1kcWT8TxMrK%2FsW%2FJCCWXU7V2r%2Brp4JUm0vVdHr35jE%2FjUo2qK4o3y5OMVuuHRI46HObKuJm%2B%7Ctkp%3ABk9SR4DXtsvkYg">here</a>
        or <a href="https://amigastore.eu/en/275-cable-null-modem-amiga.html">here</a>) or with some compromise for a
        new hardware,
        with a <a href="https://amigastore.eu/en/323-usb-floppy-emulator-gotek.html">GOTEK floppy emulator</a>. There is
        also the SDBox (SD card reader for the Parallel port), but I haven't tried it, so I can't recommend it yet.
        I tried both the null modem cable and the GOTEK though, and can recommend going for both, as you'll need the
        null modem cable anyway, and having a GOTEK makes life so much easier (just think trying out new games and
        demos). I installed my GOTEK in an external floppy case, so it looks nice.</p>

      <p>Here is <a href="https://www.amigalove.com/viewtopic.php?t=15">AmigaLove's excellent guide on AmigaExplorer</a>
        and how to transfer files with a null modem cable. It was written for an Amiga 1200, but it works on Amiga 500
        as well.</p> But you can also do it with a <a href="a500-gotek-file-transfer.html">GOTEK drive by using an
        emulator</a>. Just insert an empty ADF into the emulator's virtual floppy drive and copy stuff on it, then copy
      the ADF image to your GOTEK's USB stick.

      <p>For the Kickstart, you also have two options. You can buy a new
        Kickstart ROM (there are <a
          href="https://sordan.ie/product/550/dual-double-kickstart-rom-13--31-amiga-500-600-2000-switcher/">DUAL
          ROMs</a> too, where you can switch between
        Kickstart 1.3 and 3.1 with a physical switch to keep your system backwards compatible), or you can load the new
        Kickstart from a file, by mapping it to a memory
        location (soft-kick). I wanted to keep the original 1.3 chip in my Amiga 500, so I took the
        soft-kick route. <a href="a500-soft-kick-dual-boot.html">Click here for a guide on how to set it up</a>, and
        optionally, how to make a
        dual-boot setup between Workbench 1.3 and 3.1.</p>

      <h3>Now finally,</h3>
      <p>Here is all that's needed to bring our Amiga 500 to the Internet:</p>

      <ul>
        <li>An Amiga 500 with at least an 512Kbyte memory expansion. Or more if you're taking the soft-kick route. You
          can also do a 1MB Chip RAM mod, if you have a Rev.6A motherboard with a Fat Agnus (8372A) chip, that supports
          1Mb Chip RAM.</li>
        <li>A way to transfer files between a PC and the Amiga (a GOTEK or a null modem cable and the AmigaExplorer
          software)</li>
        <li>Kickstart 2.0+</li>
        <li>A null modem cable to connect our Amiga to a PC which will act as a PPP server.</li>
        <li>A whatever PC running Linux</li>
      </ul>
      <p>Optional (but recommended):</p>
      <ul>
        <li>A hard drive with some more extra memory (2MB will do) to install Workbench and applications.</li>
      </ul>

      <h2 id="amiga-pc-ppp">Amiga-PC PPP config</h2>

      <p>On the PC side: I used a Raspberry Pi, which is always on and has a pppd running. It's connected to the Amiga
        via a
        NullModem cable and a serial to USB adapter. An older PC that has a 9-pin female serial port would also do the
        job and you can skip the adapter. But you can find serial to USB adapters all over eBay for a very low cost.</p>

      <p>On the Amiga side: The only thing we need is a TCP/IP stack and some applications. You'll see that's a
        challenge
        in itself, as most Internet applications barely work on a 68000 CPU and 2MB of RAM.</p>

      <h2>Configure the PC side</h2>
      <p>Let's prepare the PC side first. I was using Raspberry Pi OS Lite Bullseye:</p>

      <p>Install ppp if it isn't already present:</p>
      <pre>sudo apt install ppp</pre>

      <p>Enable IP forwarding:</p>
      <pre>sudo sh -c "echo 1 > /proc/sys/net/ipv4/ip_forward"</pre>

      <p>Create a script that will set the Network Address Translation rules and start the ppp daemon:
      <p>
      <pre>nano start-amiga-ppp.sh</pre>
      <p>Paste the following to it:</p>
      <pre>#!/usr/bin/env bash
# Caution, the following two commands will clear all rules!
# Comment them out if you have rules already configured and you don't want that
        
sudo iptables -F
sudo iptables -t nat -F
        
# Configure the Network Address Translation (NAT) between PPP and your local network.
# My Raspberry Pi is connected to my local network via Wifi, so I'm using wlan0
# If you're connected via ethernet, update the commands to use eth0 instead)
        
sudo iptables -t nat -A POSTROUTING -o wlan0 -j MASQUERADE
sudo iptables -A FORWARD -i wlan0 -m state --state RELATED,ESTABLISHED -j ACCEPT
sudo iptables -A FORWARD -i ppp0 -o wlan0 -j ACCEPT
        
# Start the ppp connection
sudo pppd file /etc/ppp/amiga</pre>

      <p>Set it executable:</p>
      <pre>chmod +x start-amiga-ppp.sh</pre>

      <p>Create the /etc/ppp/amiga configuration file for pppd:</p>
      <pre>sudo nano /etc/ppp/amiga</pre>

      <p>Paste the following contents to it:</p>

      <pre># Enable connection debugging facilities
debug

# Don't detach from the controlling terminal. Without this option, 
# if a serial device other than the terminal on the standard input is specified, 
# pppd will fork to become a background process.
nodetach

# Serial device is the device used to connect to the Amiga
# In my case it's the USB-Serial adapter which I used to connect the null modem cable 
# to the Raspberry Pi's USB port.
/dev/ttyUSB0

# Baud (19200 is the maximum the Amiga 500 can handle with the serial.device)
19200
#38400
#57600
#115200

# No authentication required
noauth

# Don't use the modem control lines. With this option, pppd will ignore 
# the state of the CD (Carrier Detect) signal from the modem and will not 
# change the state of the DTR (Data Terminal Ready) signal. 
# This is the opposite of the modem option.
local

# Local and remote IP addresses and the netmask
# The Raspberry Pi will be reachable on 10.0.0.1 from the Amiga and 
# the 10.0.0.2 will be the Amiga's address. They're are not the same as your main 
# local network's address and they're arbitrary, you can make them up as you like.
# Your local network is likely in the 192.168.0.1 or similar range. 
# That's why we configured the NAT to translate between these two networks.
10.0.0.1:10.0.0.2
netmask 255.255.255.0

# Enables the "passive" option in the LCP. With this option, pppd will
# attempt to initiate a connection; if no reply is received from the
# peer, pppd will then just wait passively for a valid LCP packet from
# the peer (instead of exiting, as it does without this option).
passive

# Add an entry to this system's ARP [Address Resolution Protocol]
# table with the IP address of the peer and the Ethernet address of this system.
# This will have the effect of making the peer appear to other systems 
# to be on the local ethernet.
proxyarp

# Do not exit after a connection is terminated, try reconnecting instead
persist

# Use software flow control (i.e. XON/XOFF) to control the flow of data on the serial port.
# Much slower, better to go with RTS/CTS hardware flow control, which is the default
#xonxoff
</pre>

      <p>Run the start-amiga-ppp.sh script so that the ip forwarding rules are set and the interface is up.</p>

      <p>Optional, we can set the PPP connection up as a service:</p>

      <p>Create /etc/systemd/system/ppp-amiga.service with these contents:</p>
      <pre>
[Unit]
Description=Amiga PPP networking

[Service]
Type=simple
ExecStart=/usr/sbin/pppd file /etc/ppp/amiga

[Install]
WantedBy=multi-user.target</pre>

      <p>Reload the services, enable and start the connection:</p>
      <pre>
sudo systemctl daemon-reload
sudo systemctl enable ppp-amiga
sudo systemctl start ppp-amiga</pre>


      <pre>sudo systemctl status ppp-amiga
ppp-amiga.service - Start PPP for Amiga networking
Loaded: loaded (/etc/systemd/system/ppp-amiga.service; enabled; vendor preset: enabled)
Active: active (running) since Sat 2023-10-07 00:04:16 CEST; 5s ago
Main PID: 3324 (pppd)
Tasks: 1 (limit: 1599)
CPU: 29ms
CGroup: /system.slice/ppp-amiga.service
  3324 /usr/sbin/pppd file /etc/ppp/amiga

Oct 07 00:04:16 pi pppd[3324]: using channel 19
Oct 07 00:04:16 pi pppd[3324]: using channel 19
Oct 07 00:04:16 pi pppd[3324]: Using interface ppp0
Oct 07 00:04:16 pi pppd[3324]: Using interface ppp0
Oct 07 00:04:16 pi pppd[3324]: Connect: ppp0 <--> /dev/ttyUSB0
Oct 07 00:04:16 pi pppd[3324]: Connect: ppp0 <--> /dev/ttyUSB0
Oct 07 00:04:16 pi pppd[3324]: sent [LCP ConfReq id=0x1</pre>

      <p>Don't forget that the iptables forwarding rules are not persistent by default and need to be re-applied after
        reboot. You can make them persistent with iptables-persistent.</p>
      <p>Check the rules on the system:</p>
      <pre>sudo iptables -L</pre>
      <p>Install iptables-persistent:</p>
      <pre>sudo apt install iptables-persistent</pre>
      <p>Save the rules:</p>
      <pre>sudo iptables-save > /etc/iptables/rules.v4</pre>

      <h2>Configure the Amiga side</h2>

      <h3 id="termitetcp">Floppy only systems</h3>
      <p>There is a lightweight TCP/IP stack called TermiteTCP by Oregon Research which comes with PPP support, although
        the demo on Aminet has PPP and bsdsocket.library support turned off, so it's pretty much useless, but as all
        Oregon Research products <a href="https://eab.abime.net/showthread.php?t=54913">became public domain</a> more
        than 10 years ago, I dared to prepare a <a
          href="https://www.jottacloud.com/s/03030b6077c3132475aa5980e57906d6068">floppy installation of TermiteTCP
          version 1.50</a>, which you can grab.</a> Here is the <a
          href="https://www.jottacloud.com/s/030946fd41b4b424dc7b106f12a7a166b0b">TermiteTCP version 1.60 installer
          disk</a> too.

      <p>It's very easy to setup, although not very stable, so I can't really recommend it. It was dropping the
        connection after a few minutes despite increasing the connection timeout and verification interval, but if you
        want to play around with it, here is how I set it up:</p>

      <p>Launch TermiteTCP68k and open the connection settings from the menu. You can leave most things at default here,
        just make sure it matches the pppd settings on your PC's side:</p>
      <p><img src="../images/termitetcp_01.gif"></p>

      <p>Open the network settings. Set the local IP to 10.0.0.2 (amiga), remote to 10.0.0.1 (pc), the DNS server to
        your router's IP, which is 192.168.10.1 in my case. You can set the alternate DNS to 10.0.0.1 (pc) and pick a
        default domain, I typed just a500 there. </p>
      <p><img src="../images/termitetcp_02.gif"></p>

      <p>Click connect. TermiteTCP will ask if you want a direct serial connection, say Yes.</p>
      <p><img src="../images/termitetcp_03.gif"></p>

      <p>That's it, you're online. You can use the FTP or Telnet client provided on the disk to connect to the outside
        world.</p>
      <p><img src="../images/termitetcp_04.gif"></p>

      <p>Unfortunately you can't run a web browser without a hard drive, as all graphical browsers require either
        ClassAct or MUI and several libraries to be installed (even <a
          href="https://www.jottacloud.com/s/0305741f9c5c71349f89ecde84dfbbd2d24">AMosaic</a> needs MUI).</p>

      <h3>With a hard drive</h3>

      <p>Now you have more options. <a href="a500-soft-kick-dual-boot.html">Boot into Workbench 3.1</a> and have an <a
          href="http://aminet.net/package/util/arc/lha">Lha</a> utility at hand.</p>

      <p>I went with the demo version of the Miami 3.0b TCP/IP stack, as I used it back in the day, it has PPP support
        built-in (as opposed to AmiTCP) and can be configured easily from GUI. The demo version lets you stay online for
        60 minutes, which is enough for this test and casual use. Unfortunately there is no way to obtain the Miami
        license from legal sources, but if you want to try a TCP/IP stack that's still supported, <a
          href="http://roadshow.apc-tcp.de/index-en.php">RoadShow</a> is available from APC&TCP for 25 EUR, and it runs
        on 68000 and has PPP support built-in also. I haven't tried it, but might give it a go later.</p>

      <p>Install the following stuff and their dependencies on your Amiga if you don't have them already:</p>
      <ul>
        <li>Miami3.0b (<a href="http://aminet.net/package/comm/tcp/Miami32b2-main">main archive</a> and <a
            href="http://aminet.net/package/comm/tcp/Miami32b-000">68000 archive</a>, install it with the GTLayout GUI,
          which is more lightweight than MUI)</li>
        <li><a href="http://aminet.net/comm/misc/baudbandit1.4b.lha">Baudbandit 1.4b</a> (you can get higher speeds by
          replacing the original serial.device)</li>
        <li><a href="http://aminet.net/comm/tcp/AmiFTP.lha">AmiFTP</a> (free and lighter than AmFTP, but requires <a
            href="http://aminet.net/util/libs/mui38usr.lha">MUI</a> and <a
            href="http://aminet.net/util/libs/ReqToolsUsr.lha">ReqTools</a>)</li>
        <li>AWeb 3.5.09-68000 (<a href="http://aminet.net/comm/www/aweb_3_5_091.lha">main archive</a> and <a
            href="http://aminet.net/comm/www/AWeb-3.5.09-68000.lha">68000 archive</a>, requires <a
            href="http://aminet.net/dev/gui/ClassAct2Demo.lha">ClassAct</a>)</li>
        <li><a href="http://aminet.net/comm/www/Voyager.lha">Voyager 2.70</a> (another web browser, nicer than AWeb, but
          requires MUI.)</li>
        <li><a href="http://aminet.net/package/comm/irc/amirc_362_68000">AmIRC 3.6.2</a> (68000 version, but you might
          also want to look into older AmIRC versions that are faster)</li>
      </ul>

      <h4>Configure Miami PPP connection</h4>
      <p>Open the interface settings and set it up like this. Using built in serial PPP/CSLIP, Baud 19200 (same that you
        set in pppd on the PC side), static IP address 10.0.0.2 (the Amiga 500's IP):</p>
      <p><img src="../images/miami_ppp_01.gif"></p>

      <p>Go to the TCP/IP settings and set the hostname, real name, username, leave everything else unchecked:</p>
      <p><img src="../images/miami_ppp_02.gif"></p>

      <p>In the Modem settings and check the NullModem option:</p>
      <p><img src="../images/miami_ppp_03.gif"></p>

      <p>The PPP settings remain default, it looks like this:</p>
      <p><img src="../images/miami_ppp_04.gif"></p>

      <p>Open the Database settings and select the DNS Servers option in the Network Database. Then click Add and enter
        your router's local address, which is in my case 192.168.10.1 and also the PC's address which we configured to
        10.0.0.1 in the pppd settings:</p>
      <p><img src="../images/miami_ppp_05.gif"></p>

      <p>That's all there is to it, save the configuration as default from the menu, and you're ready to test it. Click
        Online and hope for the best. If you did everything right, it should go online. You can open a new CLI window,
        go to miami: and check if ping works to 10.0.0.1, then to an external address by typing:</p>
      <pre>miamiping www.google.com</pre>
      <p><img src="../images/miami_ping.gif"></p>

      <p>If everything works well, you can try out the BaudBandit device to get higher speeds. First, install BaudBandit
        on your Amiga. Then, set a higher baud rate in the pppd on the PC side (57600 for example) and restart the
        service. In Miami, open the Interface settings, change the interface type to "serial driver" and type in
        BaudBandit.device (pay attention to upper and lower cases, it's case sensitive!). Set the speed to the same you
        set in pppd, the flow control to RTS/CTS (same as in pppd), and serial mode 81N. All the rest is the same as
        before.</p>
      <p><img src="../images/miami_ppp_06.gif"></p>

      <p>On my system (1MB Chip RAM, 2MB Other RAM), I have 3-400Kbyte free memory after launching either AWeb or
        Voyager (while Miami is online with the GUI closed). It's possible to open a simple website though! Aminet and
        Frogfind.com works just fine. Getting a physical dual Kickstart ROM would help a bit, saving another 0.5MB of
        memory, but forget about pages that are image heavy or require SSL, that's way over the capabilities of this
        setup. It's painfully slow and not what this machine was intended for, but it works! If you want to visit sites
        that are forcing https (most sites do today), you can install a <a
          href="https://neongod.neocities.org/bluescsiv2-dayna#webone">WebOne proxy</a> on your Linux machine along the
        pppd, which can convert all https traffic to http and do other cool things to make the modern web more
        accessible from your Amiga.</p>

      <p><img src="../images/voyager.gif"></p>

      <p>With BaudBandit you can go up to 57600 baud speed on a 4 color screen, so I've been using that for FTP
        transfers. It doesn't work on a 16 color screen though (starts to drop packages), so you have to choose between
        speed or a more "colorful" browsing experience.</p>

      <p><img src="../images/amiftp.gif"></p>

      <p>What am I using all this for then? Chatting with friends on IRC brings back memories, and it's nice to be able
        to get software from Aminet or other places. I have an FTP server on my RaspberryPi for easy file exchange, and
        I can also backup files from the Amiga to the FTP. All the WB3.1 screenshots in this guide were grabbed on my
        Amiga (with <a href="http://aminet.net/package/util/cdity/CRSnap">CRSnap</a>) and transferred this way.</p>

      <p><img src="../images/amirc.gif"></p>]]></description>
    </item>
    <item>
        <title>Soft-kick and dual boot on an Amiga 500</title>
        <link>https://neongod.neocities.org/articles/a500-soft-kick-dual-boot.html</link>
        <guid>https://neongod.neocities.org/articles/a500-soft-kick-dual-boot.html</guid>
        <pubDate>Fri, 06 Dec 2024 15:27:31 GMT</pubDate>
        <description><![CDATA[    <div class="right-column column">
        <p>This is a guide on how you can soft-kick your Amiga 500 to Kickstart 3.1 and if you have a hard drive, how to set up a dual boot system.
        Note: If you have a dual-kickstart ROM with a hardware switch, you can just skip setting up mkick, and the leave out the lines for the besel utility in the startup-sequence.</p>

        <p>To soft-kick the Amiga 500 to Kickstart 3.1 you'll need 3 things:</p>
        <ul><li>Amiga 500 with some extra memory (512KByte chip RAM + 512KByte Other RAM is the minimum, but keep in mind that you'll load the new Kickstart ROM to memory, so you will end up having 0.5MB less usable RAM available)</li>
        <li>Kickstart 3.1 ROM file</li>
        <li><a href="http://aminet.net/package/util/boot/MKick19">MKick utility</a></li></ul>

        <p>Recommended:</p>
        <ul>
            <li>A hard drive (To install Workbench 3.1 and set up a dual boot system)</li>
            <li><a href="http://aminet.net/package/util/boot/BeSel">Besel utility</a></li>
        </ul>

        <h2>Floppy Only</h2>

        <p>Get the <a href="https://www.amigaforever.com/">Amiga Forever</a> package which contains all the Kickstart ROMs. Not all of the different ROMs work with mkick, so it can be a trial and error process finding the right one. I succeeded with kickstart40063.a600.</p>

        <p>Have an emulator (WinUAE or FS-UAE) ready on your PC/Mac and configure it so that you have access to a folder on your host system as an Amiga drive. Boot a Workbench 1.3 floppy up.</p>
        <p>Insert an empty ADF to DF1:</p>
        <p>Open a new shell and prepare a bootable disk:</p>
            <pre>install df1:</pre>
        <p>Unpack the mkick archive in your shared host folder and copy the contents of the mkick directory to the root of the floppy disk.</p>
        <p>Copy the kickstart40063.a600 ROM file to the root of the floppy disk.</p>
        <p>Copy the kickstart40063.a600.kshd and kickstart40063.a600.kick files from the KSHD directory to the root of the floppy disk, where the previously copied Kickstart ROM file is. So you should have 3 files there:</p>
<pre>kickstart40063.a600 -> the actual ROM file
kickstart40063.a600.kick -> binary file coming from the KSHD directory
kickstart40063.a600.kshd -> definition file from the KSHD directory
</pre>
        <p>Create the directory c, s, libs on the floppy disk.</p>
        <p>Copy SetPatch and Addbuffers to c and arp.library to the libs directory on the floppy disk:</p>
        <pre>copy c:SetPatch df1:c
copy c:Addbuffers df1:c
copy libs:arp.library df1:libs</pre>
        <p>Create a startup-sequence file in the s folder of the floppy disk:</p>
        <pre>ed df1:s/startup-sequence</pre>
        <p>Put the following lines in the script:</p>
        <pre>c:SetPatch >NIL: 
c:Addbuffers df0: 10
df0:mkick df0:kickstart40063.a600 ;double check it's the right file name!</pre>

        <p>Note: Press the ESC key to enter command mode, type "sa" and enter to save and "q" to quit.</p>

        <p>Transfer the newly prepared Kickstart disk ADF to your Amiga and load it up.</pre>

        <p>Note: Don't forget to remove the disk after Kickstart 3.1 is loaded (and your machine reboots), because if mkick loads again, it will remove the loaded Kickstart and you'll go back to 1.3.</p>

        <h2>Hard Drive</h2>

        <p>If you have a hard drive, you can go one step further and prepare a setup that will dual boot between Workbench 1.3 and 3.1.</p>

        <h3>MKick and Besel</h2>

        <p>Copy the mkick installation, the Kickstart ROM and KSHD files of the floppy you prepared to DH0:mkick/</p>

        <p>Create a DH0:S/start-mkick script file with the following contents (make sure the Kickstart ROM file name matches):</p>
<pre>echo "Soft-kicking Kickstart 3.1..."
dh0:mkick/mkick dh0:mkick/kickstart40063.a600</pre> 

        <p>Make the file executable; </p>
<pre>protect s:start-mkick RWED</pre>

        <p>Unpack the besel utility and copy besel to DH0:c/ and besel.cfg to DH0:s/</p>

         <p>Create a backup of the original besel.cfg in DH0:s/besel.cfg:</p>
<pre>rename dh0:s/besel.cfg dh0:s/besel.def_cfg</pre>
         <p>Create a new DH0:s/besel.cfg with the following content:</p>
<pre>F1 ; This is an entry for function key F1
s:start-mkick ; This is the script that should be executed</pre>

        <h3>Startup-sequence magic</h3>

        <p>To create a dual boot we'll need two partitions. One for the Workbench 1.3 system (the boot partition), and one for Workbench 3.1. This can be the same as the Work: partition as Workbench 3.1's installer allows you to install the system into a folder. In the example below Workbench 3.1 was installed to DH2, in a folder called WB31.</p>

        <p>Dual boot on Amiga is very easy. Follow these steps:</p>

        <p>First, execute the start-mkick script you made, to soft-kick your system to 3.1 (or switch your Dual-Kickstart ROM to 3.1), then</p>
        <p>Boot from the Workbench 3.1 install floppy disk and install the system to your desired location. When the install was successful, you can make some changes to your startup-sequence scripts. The system will boot from the partition that has 1.3 first (we will leave this partition as bootable), so we'll have to edit the startup sequence file on that partition.</p>

        <p>Rename the startup-sequence on the 1.3 partition:</p>
        <pre>rename dh0:s/startup-sequence dh0:s/startup-sequence-1.3</pre>

        <p>Create a new startup-sequence file there:</p>
        <pre>ed dh0:s/startup-sequence</pre>

        <p>With the following contents:</p>
        <pre>dh0:c/version graphics.library 37 ; Is the ROM newer than v2.04?
IF WARN ; NO, older
    ; Use the following section if you want to soft-kick your system.
    ; You can remove this part if you have a dual-kickstart ROM.
    echo "Workbench 1.3 will boot automatically in 3 seconds."
    echo "Hold F1 for Workbench 3.1"
    wait 3
    c:besel c:besel.cfg

    echo "Workbench 1.3 booting..."
    execute dh0:s/startup-sequence-1.3
ELSE ; YES, newer
    echo "Workbench 3.1 booting..."
    assign >nil: sys: DH1:WB31  
    assign >nil: c: DH1:WB31/c
    assign >nil: s: DH1:WB31/s
    assign >nil: l: DH1:WB31/l
    assign >nil: libs: DH1:WB31/libs
    assign >nil: devs: DH1:WB31/devs
    assign >nil: fonts: DH1:WB31/fonts
    assign >nil: envarc: DH1:WB31/prefs/env-archive
    execute DH1:WB31/s/startup-sequence
ENDIF
endcli</pre>

        <ul><li>What this will do is to check the graphics.library version.</li>
        <li>If it's older than what's in Kickstart 2.04, it will print a message to either Wait for Workbench 1.3 or Hold F1 if you want Workbench 3.1.</li> 
        <li>It will wait 3 seconds, so you have time to read the message and decide, then it will check if you're holding the F1 key with the besel utility.</li>
        <li>If you don't, the original startup-sequence-1.3 will be executed and Workbench 1.3 will boot normally.</li>
        <li>If you do, besel will run the start-mkick script, which will soft-kick your machine to Kickstart 3.1 and reboot.</li>
        <li>After the reboot, the graphics.library version check will run again, but this time it will be newer than 2.04, so you won't be asked anything. The assigns will be changed to point to where you installed Workbench 3.1, and the startup-sequence file of 3.1 will be executed.</li></ul>

        <p>Note: You might get blue colors in 3.1, as the palette is loaded from the boot partition by default. To fix this, simply open the palette preferences, load the defeault palette and save it. Next time the correct 3.1 palette will be loaded.</p>]]></description>
    </item>
    <item>
        <title>Workbench 1.3 - Enhancements and programs</title>
        <link>https://neongod.neocities.org/articles/a500-wb13-enhancements.html</link>
        <guid>https://neongod.neocities.org/articles/a500-wb13-enhancements.html</guid>
        <pubDate>Sun, 01 Dec 2024 21:39:25 GMT</pubDate>
        <description><![CDATA[    <div class="right-column column">

      <p>The first thing many who get more seriously into the Amiga retro computing hobby do is to replace the original operating system with the latest one, or at least with the latest official (3.1) version. But there is something special about keeping it original and use it like it was back in the day. Trying to get the most out of it. It's not as fancy and convenient as newer versions, that's true. But I think Workbench 1.3 is often dismissed as something unusable by modern (Amiga) standards, despite it being far more capable than you'd think.</p>

      <p>I spent quite a bit of time with making my Workbench 1.3 more nice and I would like to share my favourite tools, utilities and programs here, that will make your Amiga 500 more productive.</p>

      <p>Many will run from floppy and can be added to your Workbench 1.3 disk, but for the best result or building a whole desktop system with a combination of these, a hard drive is highly recommended. For reference, my Amiga 500 is equipped with Kickstart 1.3 and an A590 hard drive with 2MB Fast RAM.</p>

      <p>All software on this list is either public domain, shareware, free or was released under some form of free for non-commercial use licence.</p>
      <b>(Alphabetical order)</b>

      <h2>AmiDock</h2>
      <p>A small utility that lets you create a dock (vertical or horizontal) and use brushes, text or icons to add launchers to it. It's similar to later docks, but it runs on WB1.3 and is very small and fast. It has a bunch of brushes included both high-res interlaced and non-interlaced and you can pretty easily make new brushes based on them with Deluxe Paint. I consider AmiDock one of the cornerstones to make the 1.3 desktop more usable and nice.</p>
      <p>Download: <a href="http://aminet.net/package/util/boot/AmiDock" target="_blank">AmiDock.lha</a> (Aminet)</p>
      <p><img src="../images/amidock.png"></p>

      <h2>AmigaGuide</h2>
      <p>It's a hypertext utility made by Commodore. The archive on the Fred Fisk Disk contains developer examples and tools for AmigaGuide that works under Kickstart 1.3, plus a new free distribution license for AmigaGuide, amigaguide.library, WDisplay, and their icons.</p>
      <p>Download: <a href="http://aminet.net/package/misc/fish/fish-0870" target="_blank">Fred Fish Disk #870</a></p>
      <p><img src="../images/amigaguide.png"></p>

      <h2>AmigaTCP / AmigaNOS</h2>
      <p>AmigaNOS (or AmigaTCP or KA9Q) is probably the only TCP/IP stack that works on Kickstart 1.3, besides Commodore's AS225 stack. It's a port of the TCP/IP stack originally written by Phil Karn. I made a <a href="a500-amiganos.html">somewhat comprehensive guide</a> on how to set it up.</p>
      <p>Download: <a href="https://www.jottacloud.com/s/030bd8a4914b2a94e0c8cfbe3b3220a10ed" target="_blank">AmigaNOS-Complete.lha</a></p>

      <h2>AmigaTestKit</h2>
      <p>Test various functions of your Amiga that it works as it should. Comes with a bootable ADF or just copy the executable.</p>
      <p>Download: <a href="https://github.com/keirf/Amiga-Stuff/releases" target="_blank">Github release page</a></p>
      <p><img src="../images/amigatestkit.png"></p>

      <h2>ARP 1.3</h2>
      <p>The AmigaDOS Resource Project, with the aim to bring the AmigaDOS enhancements and functionality that was made available in 2.0+ back to 1.3. It adds an arp.library and a set of replacement commands for Commodore's originals, rewritten in C (instead of BCPL), while retaining compatibility.</p>
      <p>Download: <a href="http://aminet.net/package/misc/antiq/ARP_13" target="_blank">ARP_13.lha</a> (Aminet)</p></p>

      <h2>BeSel (Boot Selector)</h2>
      <p>A simple boot selector you can control with the Function keys on boot. One of the few that works on Kickstart 1.3 and can be used to make a dual boot system with newer OS versions. I <a href="a500-soft-kick-dual-boot.html">use it to</a> run mkick and load Kickstart 3.1 if I hold down F1 during boot. Very useful!</p>
      <p>Download: <a href="http://aminet.net/package/util/boot/BeSel" target="_blank">BeSel.lha (Aminet)</a></p>

      <h2>D-Copy 3.1</h2>
      <p>A popular public domain disk copier. Copies non-dos disks and comes with many features of the then commercial X-Copy for free. Can also be used with a Gotek drive to copy back ADF files to real floppies and vice versa.</p>
      <p>Download: <a href="https://aminet.net/package/disk/misc/DCopy31" target="_blank">DCopy31.lha</a></p>       
      <p><img src="../images/dcopy.png"></p>

      <h2>DirectoryOpus 4.12</h2>
      <p>Probably the most iconic two panel file manager on Amiga. Directory Opus 4 is versatile and configurable and comes with an intuitive drag and drop functionality. In 1999 the source code was released under GNU Public License. The last commercial release was 4.12, which works well on Workbench 1.3.</p>
      <p>Download: <a href="http://dopus.free.fr/files/CU_DirectoryOpus.zip" target="_blank">CU_DirectoryOpus.zip</a></p>
      <p><img src="../images/dopus.png"></p>

      <h2>DiskMaster 2.2b</h2>
      <p>DiskMaster 2.2b is the last version I found that works on Kickstart 1.3. This two panel file manager is a probably the fastest and simpliest to launch if you quickly want to manipulate some files on your system as it requires very little dependencies and resources and uses Workbench windows. It's one of the first utils I install on my Amigas. It's still under development for newer Amiga systems, but unfortunately the old V34 archive is hard to find.</p>
      <p>Download: <a href="https://chomikuj.pl/Amiga789/Amiga/Telegram+(Amiga)/Vamped+Amiga/DM2V34,7685027791.zip(archive)" target="_blank">DM2V34.zip</a></p>       
      <p><img src="../images/dm2.png"></p>

      <h2>DMouse</h2>
      <p>A tiny mouse accelerator with extra features such as a mouse blanker, auto window activator, popcli, pop window to front, push window to back, etc. Similar to QMouse.</p>
      <p>Download: <a href="http://aminet.net/package/misc/fish/fish-0421" target="_blank">Fred Fish Disk #421</a></p>

      <h2>File Master 2.2</h2>
      <p>The last version of the original file manager by Toni Wilen, the author of WinUAE, before the complete rewrite. Features include: ILBM/ascii/hex viewers, hex editor, disk editor, protracker module and audio sample players, user configurable command buttons, and more.</p>
      <p>Download: <a href="http://aminet.net/package/util/dir/FileMaster2.2" target="_blank">FileMaster2.2.lha (Aminet)</a></p>
      <p><img src="../images/filemaster2.png"></p>

      <h2>FixDisk</h2>
      <p>Ever had a checksum or other type of error on a floppy disk? FixDisk might be able to help. Works with SFS and FFS volumes and makes it possible to recover damaged (unreadable) tracks and files from a defective disk.</p>
      <p>Download: <a href="http://aminet.net/package/disk/salv/FixDisk_18" target="_blank">FixDisk_18.lha (Aminet)</a></p>
      <p><img src="../images/fixdisk.png"></p>

      <h2>HippoPlayer (HiP)</h2>
      <p>The most versatile music module player on the Amiga, that supports a myriad of formats, plugins, visualisations and works perfectly on the old blue. Very resource efficient too. My goto option to listen to music while doing some productive stuff on my Amiga.</p>
      <p>Download: <a href="https://aminet.net/package/mus/play/hippoplayer" target="_blank">hippoplayer.lha (Aminet)</a></p>
      <p><img src="../images/hip.png"></p>

      <h2>Icons for 1.3</h2>
      <p>AmigaLove made a wonderful icon package for 1.3 that contains disk (hdd, partition), drawer, tools, projects and trashcan icons. If you'd like to keep the 1.3 look'n'feel but make it a bit nicer, it's definitely worth checking out!</p>
      <p>Download: <a href="https://www.amigalove.com/viewtopic.php?t=1169" target="_blank">AmigaLove Icon Set 1.3a</a></p>

      <h2>Image-Ed</h2>
      <p>An icon editor that allows you to draw and edit images up to 150 by 90, in up to 16 colors. Allows freehand drawing, empty or filled rectangles, ellipses, triangles, lines curves, and polygons, copy, flip about x or y axis, stretching and condensing, flood fill and complement, text with selection and loading of font style, undo, magnified and normal sized images, and two active drawing screens at once. Perfect for making new icons or touching up existing ones.</p>
      <p>Download: <a href="http://aminet.net/package/misc/fish/fish-0412" target="_blank">Fred Fish Disk #412</a></p>
      <p><img src="../images/imageed.png"></p>

      <h2>Installer</h2>
      <p>The Amiga Installer utility from Commodore. V1.24 works on Workbench 1.3 and comes with full documentation and examples.</p>
      <p>Download: <a href="http://aminet.net/package/misc/fish/fish-0870" target="_blank">Fred Fish Disk #870</a></p>
      <p><img src="../images/installer.png"></p>

      <h2>MagicWB 1.3</h2>
      <p>MagicWB for 1.3 turns your Workbench 1.3 as close in look and feel to 2.0 as possible. It adds more bitplanes for more colors and changes the palette to make newer icons look nice. On the screenshot below it's running together with Zoom-Deamon, NewLook, PBar and AmiDock.</p>
      <p>Download: <a href="http://aminet.net/package/pix/mwb/MagicWB1.3" target="_blank">MagicWB1.3.lha (Aminet)</a></p>
      <p><img src="../images/magicwb13.png"></p>

      <h2>MemGauge</h2>
      <p>A small tool to display the current memory usage as a bar, similar to the disk usage bar in windows, on the left side of the Workbench screen.</p>
      <p>Download: <a href="http://aminet.net/package/misc/fish/fish-0222" target="_blank">Fred Fisk Disk #222</a></p>

      <h2>MKick</h2>
      <p>Load a new Kickstart ROM into Fast memory and use that instead of the hardware ROM chip in your machine. One of the most compatible software kicker utilities and the only one I was actually able to make work. I use it together with BeSel to make a dual boot system between Kickstart 1.3 and 3.1. Here is a guide about <a href="a500-soft-kick-dual-boot.html">how to set it up.</a></p>
      <p>Download: <a href="https://aminet.net/package/util/boot/MKick19" target="_blank">MKick19.lha (Aminet)</a></p>

      <h2>MoreRows</h2>
      <p>Need some more space on your Workbench screen? Add some more rows and make it larger. Runs from CLI and basically has the same effect as overscan on newer systems.</p>
      <p>Download: <a href="http://aminet.net/package/misc/fish/fish-0054" target="_blank">Fred Fish Disk #54</a></p>

      <h2>MyMenu</h2>
      <p>This utility written by Darin Johnson lets you create custom Workbench menus that you can open by holding the right mouse button. It's super useful as you can even create sub menus, launch WB and CLI programs just like from AmiDock. I use it for smaller utilities like formatting disks, ADF/DMS tools and activating other enhancement utilities like SimGen.</p>
      <p>Download: <a href="http://aminet.net/package/misc/fish/fish-0225" target="_blank">Fred Fish Disk #225</a></p>
      <p><img src="../images/mymenu.png"></p>

      <h2>NewLook</h2>
      <p>A utility that changes the look of the window and screen gadgets across all screens.</p>
      <p>Download: <a href="http://aminet.net/package/misc/fish/fish-0396" target="_blank">Fred Fish Disk #396</a></p>
      <p><img src="../images/newlook.png"></p>

      <h2>NoClick</h2>
      <p>Stop that annoying empty floppy drive clicking sound. Most NoClick hacks require Kickstart 2.0, this should work on Kickstart 1.3</p>
      <p>Download: <a href="http://aminet.net/package/misc/fish/fish-0241" target="_blank">Fred Fish Disk #241</a></p>

      <h2>LhA 1.38 and LZX 1.21</h2>
      <p>The Amiga standard unarchivers. The first thing to grab, as they're required for extracting everything else.</p>
      <p>Download: <a href="https://aminet.net/package/util/arc/LhA_e138" target="_blank">LhA_e138.run (Aminet)</a>, <a href="https://aminet.net/package/util/arc/lzx121r1">Lzx121r1.lha (Aminet)</a></p>

      <h2>OctaMED 4.0</h2>
      <p>A professional music tracker with 8 channel and MIDI support. A must have if you're serious about music making on the Amiga. Version 4.0 was released as free software and works perfectly even on old systems.</p>
      <p>Download: <a href="http://aminet.net/package/mus/edit/OctaMEDv4" target="_blank">OctaMEDv4.lha (Aminet)</a></p>
      <p><img src="../images/octamed.png"></p>

      <h2>PBar</h2>
      <p>Change the pattern in the title of the windows. Tired of the classic 1.3 stripes? Try some fancy new design! Comes with a set of patters and an utility to make your own.</p>
      <p>Download: <a href="http://aminet.net/package/misc/fish/fish-0396" target="_blank">Fred Fish Disk #396</a></p>
      <p><img src="../images/pbar.png"></p>

      <h2>PCalender & PClock</h2>
      <p>Small utilities to display the clock, available chip and fast memory and a calender where you can scroll through the years and months with the arrow keys.</p>
      <p>Download: <a href="http://aminet.net/package/misc/fish/fish-0396" target="_blank">Fred Fish Disk #396</a></p>
      <p><img src="../images/pcalender.png"></p>

      <h2>PPMore</h2>
      <p>A text file reader with nice features. Smooth scrolling, jump between pages. Version 1.8 even features a more WB2.0 style look and supports PowerPacker packed files (comes with the library)</p>
      <p>Download: <a href="http://aminet.net/package/misc/fish/fish-0542" target="_blank">Fred Fish Disk #542</a></p>
      <p><img src="../images/ppmore.png"></p>

      <h2>PPrefs</h2>
      <p>Preferable Preferences, which aim to replace the original Prefs program and provide an alternative UI for setting system preferences more efficiently.</p>
      <p>Download: <a href="http://aminet.net/package/misc/fish/fish-0242" target="_blank">Fred Fish Disk #242</a></p>
      <p><img src="../images/pprefs.png"></p>

      <h2>ProTracker</h2>
      <p>The legendary 4 channel music tracker. Version 2.3F contains many bugfixes, fully supports 128kB samples and comes with a bootable ADF or the executable that can be launched from Workbench. For anyone interested in .MODs or music-making on the Amiga.</p>
      <p>Download: <a href="http://github.com/8bitbubsy/pt23f" target="_blank">ProTracker 2.3F</a></p>
      <p><img src="../images/protracker.png"></p>

      <h2>QMouse</h2>
      <p>A very small and capable mouse accelerator utility, that also comes with a ton of other features like floppy a titlebar clock, screen and mouse pointer blanker, hotkeys, window click to front and more.</p>
      <p>Download: <a href="http://aminet.net/package/misc/fish/fish-0262" target="_blank">Fred Fish Disk #262</a></p>

      <h2>SimGen</h2>
      <p>This awesome program allows you to set a 2 or 4 color picture as a backdrop in Workbench 1.3. It looks like a simulated genlock (transparent windows), so that's where its name coming from: Simulated Genlock. It adds 1 or 2 bpp to the Workbench screen and loads the picture onto those bitplanes. The background image should be in an IFF format and 640x200 pixels in size. You can convert images to this format on modern computers with a tool like <a href="https://github.com/Pixinn/rgb2amiga" target="_blank">rgb2amiga</a>.</p>
      <p>Download: <a href="http://aminet.net/package/misc/fish/fish-0243" target="_blank">Fred Fish Disk #243</a></p>
      <p><img src="../images/simgen.png"></p>

      <h2>Snap (Clipboard)</h2>
      <p>Have you been missing the clipboard functionality from your Workbench 1.3? Look no further. Snap is a clipboard tool for clipping text or graphics using the clipboard device. It handles different fonts, keymaps, etc. A must have if you work with text files.</p>
      <p>Download: <a href="http://aminet.net/package/misc/fish/fish-0793" target="_blank">Fred Fish Disk #793</a></p>

      <h2>Snoopdos</h2>
      <p>Monitor what's happening when you launch an application. What resources, devices, fonts, libraries it's looking for and troubleshoot why it's not working or launching. Missing font or library? You can figure it out quickly with this tool. Version 1.5 and 1.7 works on Workbench 1.3 just fine.</p>
      <p>Download: <a href="http://aminet.net/package/misc/fish/fish-0725" target="_blank">Fred Fish Disk #725</a></p>
      <p><img src="../images/snoopdos.png"></p>

      <h2>SysInfo 4.0</h2>
      <p>The most popular system information and benchmark tool for Amiga. SysInfo has everything in one place and in a nice package. Unfortunately the latest version from Aminet doesn't work on Kickstart 1.3, but version 4.0 runs perfectly.</p>
      <p>Download: <a href="https://download.d0.se/pub/sysinfo_4.0.lha" target="_blank">Sysinfo_4.0.lha</a></p>
      <p><img src="../images/sysinfo.png"></p>

      <h2>TSGui (TrackSaver)</h2>
      <p>A nice graphical application that can create Image files (also known as ADF or HDF) from any floppy disk or 
      harddisk partition, or write ADF files back to real floppies. It supports GZIP and DMS, runs from CLI and WB and works on everything since Kickstart 1.2. Amazing piece of software and a must have if you're handling ADFs.</p>
      <p>Download: <a href="http://aminet.net/package/disk/misc/tsgui" target="_blank">tsgui.lha (Aminet)</a></p>
      <p><img src="../images/tsgui.png"></p>

      <h2>UnZip 5.40</h2>
      <p>Extract Zip files. Version 5.40 runs fine under Workbench 1.3.</p>
      <p>Download: <a href="https://aminet.net/package/util/arc/UnZip" target="_blank">UnZip.lha (Aminet)</a></p>

      <h2>WBPlane</h2>
      <p>A small utility to add or remove a bitplane to Workbench to change the depth of the screen. You can add up to 4 bitplanes (16 colors). Can be run both from WB and CLI.</p>
      <p>Download: <a href="http://aminet.net/package/misc/fish/fish-0543" target="_blank">Fred Fish Disk #543</a></p>

      <h2>WBDock</h2>
      <p>Similar to AmiDock. It's a newer software intended for newer Workbench versions, but there is a 1.3 compatible release too, which is very much appreciated. It runs slightly slower than AmiDock, but more intuitive to use. It supports icons, pop-up menus and separators and the icons can be replaced with brushes (IFF/ILBM images). Cool that we have two docks to choose from.</p>
      <p>Download: <a href="https://thomas-rapp.homepage.t-online.de/amiga/wbdock.html" target="_blank">Official page</a></p>
      <p><img src="../images/wbdock.png"></p>

      <h2>WShell</h2>
      <p>This software is a command shell replacement written by William S. Hawes, the author of AREXX. It's similar to KingCON and replaces the built in shell with a much more enhanced one. Your shell windows can have a close button, a custom prompt, file name completion (by default with pressing the ESC key), scrollbar and many more. In combination with ARP 1.3 (above) which replaces some of the AmigaDOS commands with more enhanched ones, this is the ultimate shell solution for Workbench 1.3 and is an absolute must have in my optinion.</p>
      <p>Download: <a href="http://batteman.free.fr/amiga/forum/WShell20.lha" target="_blank">WShell20.lha</a></p>
      <p><img src="../images/wshell.png"></p>

      <h2>X-Copy Professional</h2>
      <p>Version 3.4 if the legendary copy program with tons of features for formatting and copying disks between various drives. It was commercial software, but released for free in 2010 for non-commercial use. The Aminet upload contains the disk image from where you can copy it where you want.</p>
      <p>Download: <a href="http://aminet.net/package/disk/bakup/xcopy34_master_19910217" target="_blank">xcopy34_master_19910217.zip (Aminet)</a></p>
      <p><img src="../images/xcopy.png"></p>

      <h2>ZoomDaemon</h2>
      <p>Adds a third gadget to all windows to zoom in and out between two sizes. Minimize or maximize your windows quickly!</p>
      <p>Download: <a href="http://aminet.net/package/misc/fish/fish-0498" target="_blank">Fred Fish Disk #498</a></p>

      <h2>VirusZ</h2>
      <p>Virus checker that recognizes over 220 boot viruses and over 115 file viruses. The filechecker can also decrunch files for testing. The memory checker removes all known viruses from memory without 'Guru Meditation' and checks memory for viruses regularly. Version 3.0 works well on Workbench 1.2/1.3 and the archive comes with reqtools.library.13. Make sure that's what gets copied to your LIBS: assign.</p>
      <p>Download: <a href="http://aminet.net/package/misc/fish/fish-0902" target="_blank">Fred Fish Disk #902</a></p>
      <p><img src="../images/virusz.png"></p>]]></description>
    </item>
    <item>
        <title>Why Amiga 500?</title>
        <link>https://neongod.neocities.org/articles/a500-why.html</link>
        <guid>https://neongod.neocities.org/articles/a500-why.html</guid>
        <pubDate>Fri, 06 Dec 2024 15:31:30 GMT</pubDate>
        <description><![CDATA[    <div class="right-column column">

      <p>The Amiga 500 with it's 4-5 million units sold was Commodore's best selling machine after the C64 and the one
        that kept the company around for a little longer. Today it's one of the best retro computer platforms with
        advantages hard to match.</p>
      <ul>
        <li>It was the most popular Amiga model, so there are still plenty available second hand, which makes it the
          cheapest too.</li><br>
        <li>It's the simplest to get started with. Turn it on, insert a floppy and enjoy.</li><br>
        <li>Using an Amiga 500 with a Kickstart 1.3 is fun in itself. Besides the biggest game library in the Amiga
          world, there are plenty of productivity software for it too. It has software that can be still useful today
          (think DeluxePaint IV, ProTracker, OctaMed, WordPerfect).</li><br>
        <li>As it was very popular in Europe, there are lots of great games and demoscene productions made by European
          studios, groups and individuals. The limitations of the machine make it an attractive target platform for <a
            href="https://www.pouet.net/prodlist.php?platform%5B%5D=Amiga+OCS%2FECS&page=1">new
            demos</a> and <a href="https://www.indieretronews.com/search/label/Amiga">retro games</a>,
          so there are still new releases to check out from time to time.</a></li><br>
        <li>It's also the easiest to repair. There are plenty of spare parts available, and most capacitors were still
          thru-hole mounted, so it's easy to recap too if needed. The capacitors on the motherboard last much longer
          than the surface mounted ones in the newer amigas and there was no battery to leak (except on expansion boards
          or the A500+, so pay attention to those). The CPU and most custom chips are socketed and easily replacable and
          even upgradable. With some motherboard revisions you can esentially upgrade your OCS A500 into an ECS A500+.
          The keyboard uses wires and a pin connector, instead of the more vulnerable foil connector of later machines.
        </li><br>
        <li>There is even a <a href="https://www.a1200.net/shop/new-amiga-500-case/">newly produced case</a> (top and
          bottom shell) in two colors and a newly made <a href="https://www.a1200.net/amiga-mechanical-keyboard/"
           >mechanical keyboard</a> and caps.</li><br>
        <li>Very easy to expand. The Amiga 500 has a Zorro II like expansion slot on it's side, that exposes the CPU
          signals, along with other specific signals like ROM, RAM, voltage, etc. You can connect both old and new
          expansions to it, without opening up the machine. Adding a SCSI Hard Drive like the Commodore A590 or a GVP
          A500 HD+, or a versatile CPU accelerator and memory expansion board like the <a
            href="http://wiki.icomp.de/wiki/ACA500plus">ACA500Plus</a> couldn't be easier.</li><br>
        <li>There are countless new community developed hardware expansion options. If you're into hacking electronics,
          you can modify just about anything on it. HDMI video out, 68030 CPU accelerator, network adapter, WiFi modem,
          internal IDE hard drive controller with CF card support and so on.</li><br>
        <li>The hardware given it's limits is still fairly simple to understand, so if you want to get into Assembly
          prrogramming, there are great cross-platform development tools, emulators and a complete hardware reference
          manual.</li><br>
        <li>For people interested in software development, there are plenty of higher level languages as well to choose
          from: C, Amiga E, AMOS and BlitzBasic, just to name a few. There is even a <a
            href="https://github.com/earok/scorpion-editor-demos">game engine</a> under active
          development that supports both the Amiga and the Sega Genesis/MegaDrive.</li>
      </ul>

      <p>If you own an Amiga 500, I hope you'll find something useful here, and if you don't, I hope you'll get
        motivated to get one.</p>

      <p><img src="../images/amiga.lores.gif"></p>]]></description>
    </item>
    <item>
        <title>The Best B&amp;W Macintosh Games</title>
        <link>https://neongod.neocities.org/articles/best-bw-macintosh-games.html</link>
        <guid>https://neongod.neocities.org/articles/best-bw-macintosh-games.html</guid>
        <pubDate>Thu, 21 Nov 2024 10:44:01 GMT</pubDate>
        <description><![CDATA[    <div class="right-column column">

      <p>Here is my personal Top 20 List (and number of honorable mentions in an alphabetical order) of the finest
        vintage Macintosh games.
      <p>
      <p>Some aged better than the others, so I tried to focus on ones that stood the test of time and are still
        enjoyable or worth to play today, but also pick from a wide variety of genres for both casual and more hardcore
        players.</p>
      <p>If you own a vintage compact Mac and want to slow down and explore the early days of computer games, give these
        a try.</p>


      <h2 id="14">20. Dark Castle</h2>
      <img src="../images/games/darkcastle.gif">
      <p>Genre: Platform<br>
        Year: 1986<br>
        Publisher: Silicon Beach Software<br>
        Compatibility: System 1 - System 5<br>
        Download: <a href="https://macintoshgarden.org/games/dark-castle" target="_blank">Macintosh Garden</a></p>

      <p>A famous platform game on the Mac, where the player taking the role of a young hero, has to find the way
        through the rooms of a Dark Castle and defeat the evil Black Knight. The game has one of the best looking B&W
        graphics on vintage Macs and a great use of digitized sound effects. It's a very challenging game though (even
        on the beginner difficulty), filled with traps, enemies and puzzle elements. Prepare to die quickly. But
        unfortunately the biggest challenge is to launch it, as it crashes on everything above System 5. The best is to
        boot it from floppy. If you're running it in an emulator, use Mini vMac and drag the Unlocked disk image into
        the emulator's window. On the starting screen where you have to select a door, use the number keys (1, 2..).</p>

      <h2 id="20">19. Defender of the Crown</h2>
      <img src="../images/games/defenderofthecrown.gif">
      <p>Genre: Strategy<br>
        Year: 1987<br>
        Publisher: Cinemaware<br>
        Compatibility: System 1 - System 6<br>
        Download: <a href="https://macintoshgarden.org/games/defender-of-the-crown" target="_blank">Macintosh Garden</a>
      </p>

      <p>A medieval strategy game originally released on the Commodore Amiga in 1986 and ported to Macintosh in 1987. It
        set a new standard in computer game graphics. After the death of the king, different factions fight for the
        throne. The player assumes the role of a Saxon and must fight the Normans and compete against other rival lords.
        The game is map based and has several arcade mini-games (capturing the castle, fighting in tournaments, etc).
        The Macintosh version features more in-depth strategic elements compared to the original version and has very
        nice graphics despite it being 1-bit. Runs up to System 6 (it crashes at different points on newer systems). In
        2002 a <a href="https://macintoshgarden.org/games/defender-of-the-crown-digitally-remastered-edition"
          target="_blank">remastered edition</a> was released that runs on MacOS 8.1 and 9.</p>

      <h2 id="19">18. Hellcats: Over the Pacific</h2>
      <img src="../images/games/hellcats.gif">
      <p>Genre: Simulation<br>
        Year: 1991<br>
        Publisher: Graphic Simulations<br>
        Compatibility: System 6 - MacOS 9<br>
        Download: <a href="https://macintoshgarden.org/games/hellcats-over-the-pacific" target="_blank">Macintosh
          Garden</a></p>

      <p>Hellcats is a flight combat simulator with 3D graphics taking place in the WWII era. The player is piloting a
        Grumman F6F Hellcat airplane and has to complete land and flight carrier based missions with guns and bombs. It
        requires at least 2MB RAM and a 68020 processor, but runs fine in B&W. The game was a huge hit and it won
        several awards like the "Best Simulation Game" of MacWorld.</p>

      <h2 id="18">17. Cyberblast</h2>
      <img src="../images/games/cyberblast.gif">
      <p>Genre: Action, shooter<br>
        Year: 1992<br>
        Publisher: Innerprise Software, Inc.<br>
        Compatibility: System 7 - 7.6<br>
        Download: <a href="https://macintoshgarden.org/games/cyberblast" target="_blank">Macintosh Garden</a></p>

      <p>Cyberblast is a Gauntlet clone (see honorable mentions), a top-down shooter, where the player races against
        time and must make it through 64 different levels filled with enemies, collect crystals, ID-cards, extra
        weapons, etc, until he can find the missing control chip and and stop the crazy portal experiment that
        threathens our solar system. There are two characters with different abilities and limitations to select from.
        Even though the game was released the Amiga as well, the Macintosh version has a faster paced gameplay. It
        requires at least a 68020 CPU and System 7 however.</p>

      <h2 id="17">16. Lemmings</h2>
      <img src="../images/games/lemmings.gif">
      <p>Genre: Puzzle<br>
        Year: 1991<br>
        Publisher: Psygnosis<br>
        Compatibility: System - MacOS 9<br>
        Download: <a href="https://macintoshgarden.org/games/lemmings-oh-no-more-lemmings" target="_blank">Macintosh
          Garden</a></p>

      <p>Fast paced puzzle game where you have to save the lemmings through 120 different levels, using various
        abilities like drilling, climbing, gliding, building bridges, etc. The game has been ported to countless
        platforms, the B&W Mac version is obviously not being the nicest, but it's still great and an all-time classic!
      </p>

      <h2 id="16">15. Continuum</h2>
      <img src="../images/games/continuum.gif">
      <p>Genre: Arcade, Shooter<br>
        Year: 1987<br>
        Publisher: The Wilson Brothers<br>
        Compatibility: System 1-7 - MacOS 9<br>
        Download: <a href="https://macintoshgarden.org/games/prince-of-persia" target="_blank">Macintosh Garden</a></p>

      <p>Asteroids like shooter in a maze. You turn your ship, can apply thrust and use your shield or lasers to get
        through the various levels. It also features a level editor. The difficulty level can be frustrating at times,
        but it's still very well done and one of the best shooters available for vintage Macs.</p>

      <h2 id="15">14. ZOA: Zone of Avoidance</h2>
      <img src="../images/games/zoa.gif">
      <p>Genre: Arcade, Shooter<br>
        Year: 1993<br>
        Publisher: Casady & Greene<br>
        Compatibility: System 6 - 7.6<br>
        Download: <a href="https://macintoshgarden.org/games/zoa-the-zone-of-avoidance" target="_blank">Macintosh
          Garden</a></p>

      <p>This is a great space shooter with fast 3D graphics. The space station orbiting a planet is under attack by
        aliens and you're the only one who can stop them. The ship is controlled by the mouse and the game works nice in
        B&W. I would recommend it to anyone who has a slightly faster vintage Mac and likes 3D shooters, it's a well
        done game and still enjoyable today.</p>

      <h2 id="13">13. Loom</h2>
      <img src="../images/games/loom.gif">
      <p>Genre: Adventure<br>
        Year: 1990<br>
        Publisher: LucasArts<br>
        Compatibility: System 6 - MacOS 9<br>
        Download: <a href="https://macintoshgarden.org/games/loom" target="_blank">Macintosh Garden</a></p>

      <p>Exceptionally well programmed fantasy point'n'click adventure game, that runs on almost all vintage Mac
        systems, in either B&W or 16 color mode. It features a unique concept of no inventory or items to carry around.
        The player manipulates the objects on screen by interacting with them and uses spells, which most of the puzzles
        in the game are built on. It also has three difficulty levels to choose from, affecting the interface, how many
        names and marks are displayed.</p>

      <h2 id="12">12. Crystal Quest</h2>
      <img src="../images/games/crystalquest.gif">
      <p>Genre: Arcade Shooter<br>
        Year: 1987<br>
        Publisher: Casady & Greene<br>
        Compatibility: System 1 - System 7<br>
        Download: <a href="https://macintoshgarden.org/games/crystal-quest" target="_blank">Macintosh Garden</a></p>

      <p>A space shooter where you control a strange round ship (ball?) and have to collect all crystals on the screen
        for the exit to open, while enemies enter from different directions. You can also shoot in the direction you're
        going. Fast paced, addictive and supports both B&W and color mode. It won MacWorld's best action game of 1988.
      </p>

      <h2 id="11">11. Oregon Trail</h2>
      <img src="../images/games/oregontrail.gif">
      <p>Genre: Simulation<br>
        Year: 1992<br>
        Publisher: MEEC (Minnesota Educational Computing Consortium)<br>
        Compatibility: System 6 - MacOS 9<br>
        Download: <a href="https://macintoshgarden.org/games/the-oregon-trail" target="_blank">Macintosh Garden</a></p>

      <p>An educational simulation game with the intention to teach the history and realities of the emigration that
        took place in 19th century along the 3490 km long wagon route in the United States. The first version of the
        game was developed in 1971 and it was a text based. The 1992 Macintosh version features nice B&W graphics and
        animations and an engaging gameplay. The player can choose a starting character profession (banker, carpenter,
        or farmer), which determines the amount of money the party will have and thus the difficulty of the adventure.
        The player travelling through the trail will encounter dangers (bandits, snakes, etc), get through rivers with
        the caravan, repair the wagons, deal with the weather and illnesses, hunt for food and trade in cities. One of
        the most well known and iconic vintage Macintosh games, a must play.</p>

      <h2 id="10">10. Pipe Dream</h2>
      <img src="../images/games/pipedream.gif">
      <p>Genre: Puzzle<br>
        Year: 1989<br>
        Publisher: Lucasfilm Games<br>
        Compatibility: System 6 - MacOS 8.1<br>
        Download: <a href="https://macintoshgarden.org/games/pipe-dream" target="_blank">Macintosh Garden</a></p>

      <p>Also known as Pipe Mania in the EU, is an arcade style puzzle game where you must build a pipe system from the
        given pipe shapes quickly before and while the water starts flowing. It's a race against time, thinking ahead,
        to build a pipe long enough with corners and junctions so that you get enough points to reach the next level.
        Full screen, good graphics, with fun music and sound effects. Simple, but very challenging puzzle game.</p>

      <h2 id="9">9. Arkanoid</h2>
      <img src="../images/games/arkanoid.gif">
      <p>Genre: Arcade<br>
        Year: 1988<br>
        Publisher: Taito<br>
        Compatibility: System 2 - System 6<br>
        Download: <a href="https://macintoshgarden.org/games/arkanoid" target="_blank">Macintosh Garden</a></p>

      <p>An absolute classic breakout game that makes the original much more fun by reimagining the bat as a spaceship
        and adding power-ups like lasers, a catching device and slow down, to make the gameplay more arcade like. The
        game has very nice B&W graphics, animations and digital sound effects. It uses a framebuffer, which can have
        issues if there are many memory residents running, so in case it complains, try to launch it from a minimal
        System 6 installation, or boot it from floppy.</p>

      <h2 id="8">8. Sim City</h2>
      <img src="../images/games/simcity.gif">
      <p>Genre: Simulation, Strategy<br>
        Year: 1989<br>
        Publisher: Maxis<br>
        Compatibility: System 6 - MacOS 9<br>
        Download: <a href="https://macintoshgarden.org/games/simcity" target="_blank">Macintosh Garden</a></p>

      <p>I guess I don't need to introduce this one. The father of all open-ended strategic simulation games. The very
        first in the "Sims" series. Become the major of an existing city and help to make it prosper, or build your
        dream city from the ground up. Manage the infrastructure and ecomony and deal with natural disasters like
        floods, fires, earthquakes, etc. Such a timeless concept and game, that it's a must have if you like the genre.
      </p>

      <h2 id="7">7. ShufflePuck Cafe</h2>
      <img src="../images/games/shufflepuckcafe.gif">
      <p>Genre: Arcade, Sport<br>
        Year: 1988<br>
        Publisher: Broderbund<br>
        Compatibility: System 1 - 7<br>
        Download: <a href="https://macintoshgarden.org/games/shufflepuck-cafe" target="_blank">Macintosh Garden</a></p>

      <p>Air hockey game with the atmosphere of the cantina from Star Wars. The player can choose an opponent from
        various alien creatures with different difficulty levels and play styles. Some of them can be very challening,
        so it's worth to try playing with changing some of the paddle parameters like sideways and forward bounce and
        power, size, etc. You can also add a moving brick in the middle of the field as an extra twist. I played this
        game during countless of school breaks in the computer room, and loved the atmosphere and the animations. It
        runs perfectly on my Mac Classic II with System 7.0.1. An interesting addition is that there was an unofficial
        version of the game that contained mild nudity, where Princess Bejin exposes her breast when she raises her
        hand. This version became so widespread that many belived that it was a feature of the original.</p>

      <h2 id="6">6. Test Drive II: The Duel</h2>
      <img src="../images/games/testdrive2.gif">
      <p>Genre: Racing, Simulation<br>
        Year: 1989<br>
        Publisher: Accolade<br>
        Compatibility: System 6 - System 7.6<br>
        Download: <a href="https://macintoshgarden.org/games/the-duel-test-drive-ii" target="_blank">Macintosh
          Garden</a></p>

      <p>Probably the best car driving simulator on vintage Macs. You race supercars like the Ferrari F40 or the Porsche
        959 against the clock or a computer opponent on various tracks, while avoiding the police and keeping track when
        to stop for refuel. There were extension disks for more cars (muscle cars and super cars disk) and more
        sceneries as well (California and European challenge). The game has very nice graphics and on faster machines
        (like the SE/30 or the Classic II) runs very smoothly. Even though it was released on many other platforms, I
        think the Macintosh version was done well and is still very much enjoyable.</p>

      <h2 id="5">5. Glider 4.0</h2>
      <img src="../images/games/glider4.gif">
      <p>Genre: Arcade, Casual<br>
        Year: 1991<br>
        Publisher: Soft Dorothy Software<br>
        Compatibility: System 6 - MacOS 8.1<br>
        Download: <a href="https://macintoshgarden.org/games/glider-40" target="_blank">Macintosh Garden</a></p>

      <p>Fly a paperplane across the house, catch the warm air to give you a lift, but avoid the obstacles and dangers.
        Arcade game requiring good timing skills with a non-violent and addictive gameplay. Many side-scrolling rooms to
        explore, multiple directions to go, lots of creative ideas and fun animations, extendable with new levels and
        comes with a level designer included. Macintosh original, a true classic.</p>

      <h2 id="4">4. Pools of Darkness</h2>
      <img src="../images/games/poolsofdarkness.gif">
      <p>Genre: Role playing<br>
        Year: 1992<br>
        Publisher: Strategic Simulations Inc.<br>
        Compatibility: System 6 - MacOS 9<br>
        Download: <a href="https://macintoshgarden.org/games/the-duel-test-drive-ii" target="_blank">Macintosh
          Garden</a></p>

      <p>It's a role playing game set in the Dungeons and Dragons universe, with a dungeon crawler and isometric
        turn-based battle mechanic. It's the fourth and final entry of the Pool of Radiance series, but the story is
        playable in itself. Set in the Forgotten Realms, the player has to stop an evil god from invading the land of
        Phlan, travelling between dimensions, fighting his minions. There is a pre-designed party, but you can also
        create your own. Originally released for MS-DOS and then the Amiga, I think the Macintosh version is what makes
        the most out of this engine and the 'cutscenes' feature some gorgeous 1-bit graphics. During the combat the
        player goes one by one through characters, assigning them various commands. The battles are challenging, you
        must really think how you fight. The game comes on two floppies, one for the B&W and one for the Color graphics.
      </p>

      <h2 id="3">3. Indiana Jones and the Last Crusade</h2>
      <img src="../images/games/indy3.gif">
      <p>Genre: Adventure<br>
        Year: 1990<br>
        Publisher: Lucasfilm Games<br>
        Compatibility: System 6 - MacOS 9<br>
        Download: <a href="https://macintoshgarden.org/games/indiana-jones-and-the-last-crusade"
          target="_blank">Macintosh Garden</a></p>

      <p>Point'n'click adventure game, using the SCUMM engine. It mostly follows the story of the film, with lots of
        places to visit, puzzles to solve and jokes to laugh at. It has both 16 color and B&W support, with nicely done
        B&W graphics (as opposed to most Sierra games, where the B&W mode was best effort) and an engaging gameplay with
        sane and logical puzzles. There are multiple ways to solve them too, which give the game some replay value. I
        would argue that this is the best point'n'click adventure game on B&W Macs.</p>


      <h2 id="2">2. Prince of Persia</h2>
      <img src="../images/games/princeofpersia.gif">
      <p>Genre: Platform<br>
        Year: 1992<br>
        Publisher: Broderbund<br>
        Compatibility: System 6 - MacOS 9<br>
        Download: <a href="https://macintoshgarden.org/games/prince-of-persia" target="_blank">Macintosh Garden</a></p>

      <p>An iconic platform game and one of the first games to use a cinematic style animation. The game combines run &
        jump platform mechanics with areas requiring careful steps and enemies with a sword fighting combat. Jaffar
        wants to marry the princess but she refuses. He gives her 60 minutes to change her mind or die. The protagonist,
        whom the princess loves, is thrown into prison. He must get out and rescue the princess before the time runs
        out. I've spend countless of hours trying to beat the game with my friends in our school. The B&W Macintosh
        version looks fantastic and is a joy to play even today.</p>

      <h2 id="1">1. Tetris</h2>
      <img src="../images/games/tetris.gif">
      <p>Genre: Puzzle<br>
        Year: 1988<br>
        Publisher: Spectrum HoloByte<br>
        Compatibility: System 6 - MacOS 9<br>
        Download: <a href="https://macintoshgarden.org/games/prince-of-persia" target="_blank">Macintosh Garden</a></p>

      <p>The original version of the world famous Tetris game, an absolute classic and a masterpiece. It features
        everything that made this game so great. Challenging puzzle, good music and graphics (the background images
        change as you level up), and that "it takes 2 minutes to learn, but a lifetime to master." A must have.</p>

      <br><br>
      <h1 id="honorablementions">Honorable Mentions<h1>

          <h2 id="21">Battle Chess</h2>
          <img src="../images/games/battlechess.gif">
          <p>Genre: Chess<br>
            Year: 1991<br>
            Publisher: Interplay<br>
            Compatibility: System 6 - MacOS 9<br>
            Download: <a href="https://macintoshgarden.org/games/battle-chess" target="_blank">Macintosh Garden</a></p>

          <p>It was so exciting back then to see chess coming to life! Battle Chess is technically a conventional chess
            game, with animated pieces. Every piece has a different animation and battle style, depending on whom they
            fight with. There are 10 skills levels and an option to switch to a 2D board without animations (even during
            play). If you like chess, you have to try this. If you don't, still do because the animations are so funny.
          </p>

          <h2 id="22">The Colony</h2>
          <img src="../images/games/colony.gif">
          <p>Genre: FPS<br>
            Year: 1988<br>
            Publisher: Mindscape<br>
            Compatibility: System 1 - 6<br>
            Download: <a href="https://macintoshgarden.org/games/the-colony" target="_blank">Macintosh Garden</a></p>

          <p>The Colony is probably among the very first real time FPS games, that allow the player to move freely. The
            player takes the role of the commander of a spaceship, who receives a distress signal and while
            investigating it, crash lands on a planet. You must explore the colony, repair your ship and eventually stop
            the invasion of an alien race. The game is mouse controlled (3D movement and interaction with objects),
            which can be frustrating at times, but nonetheless a very impressive game that was ahead of it's time.</p>

          <h2 id="23">Cosmic Osmo</h2>
          <img src="../images/games/cosmicosmo.gif">
          <p>Genre: Adventure<br>
            Year: 1989<br>
            Publisher: Cyan<br>
            Compatibility: System 6 - MacOS 9<br>
            Download: <a href="https://macintoshgarden.org/games/cosmic-osmo" target="_blank">Macintosh Garden</a></p>

          <p>An unconventional point'n'click adventure game intended for smaller children, based on Hypercard, from the
            creators who later worked on Myst. The game has no goal and no scoring or inventory system. It focuses on
            the joy of exploration, surprise and discovering secrets.</p>


          <h2 id="24">Gauntlet</h2>
          <img src="../images/games/gauntlet.gif">
          <p>Genre: Action, shooter<br>
            Year: 1989<br>
            Publisher: Mindscape<br>
            Compatibility: System 6<br>
            Download: <a href="https://macintoshgarden.org/games/gauntlet" target="_blank">Macintosh Garden</a></p>

          <p>Top-down hack and slash dungeon crawler game, ported from the arcade version, with an unlimited supply of
            monsters. Go through dungeons, pick up treasures, unlock doors and kill monsters. The game supports up to 4
            players and both mouse and keyboard control.</p>

          <h2 id="25">Grand Prix Circuit</h2>
          <img src="../images/games/grandprix.gif">
          <p>Genre: Racing<br>
            Year: 1989<br>
            Publisher: Accolade<br>
            Compatibility: System 6 - 7<br>
            Download: <a href="https://macintoshgarden.org/games/grand-prix-circuit" target="_blank">Macintosh
              Garden</a></p>

          <p>Formula One racing game, presumably using the same engine as Test Drive (released the same year). The game
            features 8 tracks and 3 different cars (Ferrari, McLaren, Williams) to choose from. You have to run a
            qualifying race first, then race against opponents, but be careful, the car can crash. A very enjoyable
            racing game, that runs smooth on faster B&W Macs.</p>

          <h2 id="26">Grid Wars</h2>
          <img src="../images/games/gridwars.gif">
          <p>Genre: Arcade<br>
            Year: 1985<br>
            Publisher: Ann Arbor Softworks<br>
            Compatibility: System 1 - 6<br>
            Download: <a href="https://macintoshgarden.org/games/grid-wars" target="_blank">Macintosh Garden</a></p>

          <p>Similar in concept to Shufflepuck Cafe (which this game predates), where you start from a Star Wars like
            cantina to pick your alien opponents, but the game itself is very different. It feels like a mash up of
            Space Invaders, Centipede and Tetris. The opponent builds blocks the player must shoot before they reach the
            other side. There is also a shield for each row which wears down from bouncing objects. Interesting concept
            and a very fun game. The disk contains a minimal System and boots from floppy.</p>

          <h2 id="27">Might and Magic II: Gates to Another World</h2>
          <img src="../images/games/mightandmagic2.gif">
          <p>Genre: Role Playing<br>
            Year: 1988<br>
            Publisher: New World Computing<br>
            Compatibility: System 6 - System 7.6<br>
            Download: <a href="https://macintoshgarden.org/games/might-and-magic-2" target="_blank">Macintosh Garden</a>
          </p>
          <p>Also known as Might and Magic Book Two. It's a battle focused role-playing game, with turn based combat.
            The player creates a party with up to six characters from 8 classes (Knight, Paladin, Archer, Cleric,
            Sorcerer, Robber, Barbarians and Ninjas) and adventures through the land of CRON. The game improves on the
            first one on many ways, nicer graphics, easier navigation and gameplay elements like a "delay" selector,
            which allowed for faster or slower response times and a spinning icon to notify when input from the player
            is required. It runs in a small window, but features nice graphics and a dungeon crawler mechanics with a
            fast paced gameplay.</p>

          <h2 id="28">Pararena</h2>
          <img src="../images/games/pararena.gif">
          <p>Genre: Sport<br>
            Year: 1990<br>
            Publisher: Soft Dorothy Software<br>
            Compatibility: System 6 - MacOS 9<br>
            Download: <a href="https://macintoshgarden.org/games/pararena" target="_blank">Macintosh Garden</a></p>

          <p>It's an unusual sport game, where two players compete in a parabolic arena, flying on hoverboards, trying
            to score a ball into the goals on the sides. You can gather a momentum and toss the other player out, but
            you must be careful not to kick the ball out as that gives penalties. With having only a mouse control
            option, it's not an easy game to play, you need to get the hang of it.</p>

          <h2 id="29">Police Quest: In Pursuit of the Death Angel</h2>
          <img src="../images/games/policequest.gif">
          <p>Genre: Adventure<br>
            Year: 1988<br>
            Publisher: Sierra<br>
            Compatibility: System 6 - System 7.6<br>
            Download: <a href="https://macintoshgarden.org/games/police-quest" target="_blank">Macintosh Garden</a></p>

          <p>Police Quest is a more serious take on adventure games from Sierra, that revolves around regular police
            work. Investigate crime scenes, following duty procesures, and eventually stopping a drug gang ruining the
            city. There is less focus on traditional puzzle elements and more on figuring out the right procedures (like
            you have to pull your gun before firing, or you will shoot yourself, or you have to check the police car
            before getting in, etc). Despite it has a command line interface, the story is very engaging. I played
            through the Amiga version, which is closer to the color Macintosh version and it's one of my favourite
            adventure games. The game is playable in B&W too, but unfortunately just like with Leisure Suite Larry, you
            can feel on it that the graphics wasn't optimized for it.</p>

          <h2 id="30">Sands of Fire</h2>
          <img src="../images/games/sandsoffire.gif">
          <p>Genre: Simulator<br>
            Year: 1989<br>
            Publisher: Three-Sixty Pacific<br>
            Compatibility: System 6<br>
            Download: <a href="https://macintoshgarden.org/games/sands-of-fire" target="_blank">Macintosh Garden</a></p>

          <p>WWII combat tank simulator, where you can pilot several different tanks against the German forces. You can
            control just one tank or several in formation, playing a tactics. You have to separately control the
            movement of the tank and the turrent, assuming both roles. The game features diverse missions, a training
            mode, a decent amount of realism and nice B&W graphics and sounds.</p>

          <h2 id="31">Space Quest III: The Pirates of Pestulon</h2>
          <img src="../images/games/spacequest3.gif">
          <p>Genre: Adventure<br>
            Year: 1989<br>
            Publisher: Sierra On-Line<br>
            Compatibility: System 6 - System 7.6<br>
            Download: <a href="https://macintoshgarden.org/games/space-quest-3" target="_blank">Macintosh Garden</a></p>

          <p>The game combines point'n'click and text adventure elements. The mouse is used for moving around, but text
            commands are used to interact with objects. It also has some arcade mini-games like Astro Chicken (think
            Lunar Lander) and ship-to-ship combat. The game takes place in a world which feels like a parody of Star
            Wards and Star Trek, and continues the story of Roger Wilco, who while drifting in space in hibernation,
            gets picked up by a garbage freighter. It has a much nicer graphics compared to other B&W Sierra titles. If
            you've trouble starting the game, try the SQ3 Patch 1 by Enrico Zoxx, which makes it work on newer systems.
          </p>

          <h2 id="32">Star Wars</h2>
          <img src="../images/games/starwars.gif">
          <p>Genre: Arcade<br>
            Year: 1989<br>
            Publisher: Broderbund<br>
            Compatibility: System 1 - 7.6<br>
            Download: <a href="https://macintoshgarden.org/games/star-wars" target="_blank">Macintosh Garden</a></p>

          <p>Macintosh port of the original 1983 arcade Star Wars game. You control an X-Wing during the battle at the
            Death Star and have to shoot down the Tie Fighters. The game is mouse controlled and has a simple vector
            graphics. Simple and fun, runs well on all vintage Macs.</p>

          <h2 id="33">Leisure Suit Larry 1: In the Land of the Lounge Lizards</h2>
          <img src="../images/games/larry1.gif">
          <p>Genre: Adventure<br>
            Year: 1988<br>
            Publisher: Sierra On-Line<br>
            Compatibility: System 6 - System 7.6<br>
            Download: <a href="https://macintoshgarden.org/games/leisure-suit-larry-1-original"
              target="_blank">Macintosh Garden</a></p>

          <p>Originally developed for Apple II and MS-DOS, later ported to many other platforms. An 'adult' comedy
            graphic adventure game, following a middle-aged guy named Larry, trying to get laid. He is still a virgin,
            living with his mother, and decides to visit the city of Lost Wages to try his luck in finding the woman of
            his dreams. The game is controlled with the mouse (movement) and a text parser go give commands and interact
            (talk to man, open window, etc). Even though the Macintosh version doesn't look that nice graphically, it's
            a must have for anyone owning a B&W Mac and being interested in the genre and the history of point'n'click
            adventure games.</p>

          <h2 id="34">Vette!</h2>
          <img src="../images/games/vette.gif">
          <p>Genre: Racing, Simulation<br>
            Year: 1991<br>
            Publisher: Spectrum HoloByte<br>
            Compatibility: System 6 - System 7.6<br>
            Download: <a href="https://macintoshgarden.org/games/vette" target="_blank">Macintosh Garden</a></p>

          <p>Race a Chevrolet Corvette through the streets of San Francisco. The game features the full city completely
            3D rendered and you're free to drive around and explore, which was a big deal back then! The player can
            drive through bridges, tunnels, highways and visit attractions like the Golden Gate Bridge, with full
            control of the camera views.</p>]]></description>
    </item>
    <item>
        <title>BlueSCSI v2 with an A590&apos;s external SCSI port</title>
        <link>https://neongod.neocities.org/articles/bluescsiv2-a590.html</link>
        <guid>https://neongod.neocities.org/articles/bluescsiv2-a590.html</guid>
        <pubDate>Sun, 01 Dec 2024 22:15:28 GMT</pubDate>
        <description><![CDATA[    <div class="right-column column">

        <p>I have a BlueSCSI v2 external DB25 version and as the Commodore A590 sidecar hard drive for my Amiga 500 also has a DB25 port on it's back, 
		I thought it would be good to use it as a backup of the internal SCSI drive and maybe as a means of file transfer too. It turned out to be very 
		easy, even though not without some inconveniences.</p>
		<p>The first thing is that the 3D printed case has to be removed from the BlueSCSI v2, as with the case on it won't fit on the DB25 port due to the power plug being too close. With the case removed, it fits nicely. Another issue is that the SD card slot is facing the power plug, so you can't swap the SD card without either unplugging the BlueSCSI or the power plug first. Besides these two issues however, I couldn't find anything else really. It just works great!</p>
		<p><img src="../images/bluescsi_a590_1.png"></p>
		<p>The steps I did:</p>
		<p>First I created a bluescsi.ini based on the <a href="https://bluescsi.com/docs/Compatibility">documentation</a> with these contents:</p>
		<pre>[SCSI]
System="Generic"
EnableSCSI2=0 ; Off
PrefetchBytes=0
[SCSI0]
Vendor=Blue
Product=Bluedrive
Version=1.0
SectorsPerTrack=32
HeadsPerCylinder=1</pre>
		<p>Then I used FS-UAE to create an empty 250MB hard file, which I copied to the SD card with the following file name:</p>
		<pre>HD2 - AmigaWB13.hda</pre>
		<p>Plugged the SD card in the BlueSCSI and plugged the BlueSCSI into the DB25 port of the A590 and fired it up. Using the HDToolBox from the A590 installation floppy disk
		it could find the BlueSCSI drive right away and I could partition it. I created two partitions to back up my WB and Work partitions on my internal SCSI drive, then I formatted them
		using FastFileSystem. I made the backup WB partition bootable with a reduced boot priority so I can start the system from the BlueSCSI also if anything would go wrong 
		with the internal drive and so I can boot it with an emulator.</p>
		<p><img src="../images/bluescsi_a590_2.png"></p>
		<p>What was left to do was to copy the files over with a file manager. I tried loading the disk image with FS-UAE and it works nicely, so I can actually copy new stuff to it and use
		the SD card as a means of file transfer.</p>]]></description>
    </item>
    <item>
        <title>BlueSCSI v2 and Internet on a Mac Classic II</title>
        <link>https://neongod.neocities.org/articles/bluescsiv2-dayna.html</link>
        <guid>https://neongod.neocities.org/articles/bluescsiv2-dayna.html</guid>
        <pubDate>Sun, 01 Dec 2024 22:11:02 GMT</pubDate>
        <description><![CDATA[    <div class="right-column column">

        <p>Now that I've renovated my Macintosh Performa 200 (Classic II), I wanted to put some software on it. Apple used a 1.44MB PC compatible floppy drive (SuperDrive) in the Classic II, so one way is to buy a USB floppy drive and some floppy disks and it's possible to transfer files that way, but I wanted a faster and more flexible solution and that's where the BlueSCSI comes into the picture.</p>

        <p>BlueSCSI is a project that aims to create an open source SCSI solution for vintage computers. It's mainly driven by Apple enthusiasts, so it has vintage Macs in mind as default, but of course it works with many other systems too. BlueSCSI v2 is a completely redesigned board that's based around the Raspberry Pi Pico microcontroller. It also shares some code with ZuluSCSI's SCSI2SD implementation.<p/>

        <p>The reason I chose BlueSCSI instead of ZuluSCSI or the Pi/RASCSI project is that I was mainly aiming to use it on Mac and the possibility of accessing the Internet with it was also appealing. Not to mention the cost, which is very reasonable, from 34 EUR for a build it yourself kit.</p>

        <p><img src="../images/BlueSCSI-kit-1.jpg"></p>

        <p>BlueSCSI comes in different form factors, for both internal or external use. I decided to pick up the DB25 connector version (external unit), as I didn't want to replace my internal hard drive (yet), and I was afraid that the wireless capabilities would be impacted if I would install it inside the Mac's housing. The DB25 unit comes with a 3D printed case, it has SCSI termination installed and enabled by default and it connects to the SCSI port on the back of your Mac. I got the kit, which had to be assembled, which was pretty easy. The SMD components are already soldered on, so what's left is to solder on the DB25 connector and the connector for the Raspberry Pi Pico W (which comes included with the kit).</p>
        <div class="image-row">
        <img src="../images/BlueSCSI-kit-2.jpg"><img src="../images/BlueSCSI-kit-3.jpg">
        </div>]]></description>
    </item>
    <item>
        <title>The BRG MK27 portable cassette player and recorder</title>
        <link>https://neongod.neocities.org/articles/brg-mk27-portable-cassette-player.html</link>
        <guid>https://neongod.neocities.org/articles/brg-mk27-portable-cassette-player.html</guid>
        <pubDate>Wed, 20 Nov 2024 14:44:48 GMT</pubDate>
        <description><![CDATA[    <div class="right-column column">
      <p>I found this absolute gem in my father's garage. I remember using this when I was like 6 or 7 years old. I
        thought it will be a fun project to make it work again, but then, I plugged it in and it works just fine!
        Amazing. It's from 1977 and must have been in storage for more than 30 years, but it still plays perfectly. I
        gave it a clean and now I have a portable cassette player too!</p>

      <a href="../images/collection/brgmk27_1_1.jpg" target="_blank"><img src="../images/collection/brgmk27_1.jpg"></a>

      <p>BRG stands for Budapesti Radiotechnikai Gyar (Budapest Radiotechnic Factory), one of the major radio equipment
        manufacturers on the Soviet market. The MK series was intended as a portable boombox for camping, weekend
        houses, etc. The MK27 was designed in 1975 and first available for consumers in 1977. Featuring a funky,
        youngful, but slightly militaristic design, with rubber buttons. Even though it's look was controversial (some
        called it a "diver" or a "space" magnetofon), it's unique for sure and it became rather popular and widespread
        in Hungary after it's release.</p>
      </p>

      <p>It has a 0.8W power output, weights 1.3 kg and runs on batteries (5 x R14, 7.5V) and a power adapter. The tape
        mechanism is BRG's own design, simple and robust, but not without issues. Forwarding/Rewinding should be used
        carefully as it doesn't have an auto-stop function and the torque is rather strong, so if left unattended, it
        can stretch or damage the tape.</p>

      <a href="../images/collection/brgmk27_2_1.jpg" target="_blank"><img src="../images/collection/brgmk27_2.jpg"></a>

      <p>There are 5 control buttons, Forward, Play, Stop/Eject, Record, Rewind, the icons on them are not easy to
        understand though, the Play button facing "up" if the unit in a lying position and the Record having an inverse
        play symbol and facing "down". It's easy to mix them up and accidentaly press Record. The player can be operated
        in both standing and lying position, all the labels however are designed to face the user in the lying position,
        except the technical label on the back.</p>

      <p>There is a power adapter plug and a 5pin DIN input connector on one side and a volume control slider on the
        other side. The handle can be removed by pressing the two big PAT buttons on the sides simultanously and pulling
        the handle out.</p>

      <a href="../images/collection/brgmk27_3_1.jpg" target="_blank"><img src="../images/collection/brgmk27_3.jpg"></a>

      <p>The sound quality of the unit is what you would expect from a player of this era and segment. It's not anywhere
        near good, but it's fine for casual listening. Overall it's a very nice piece of cassette player history I would
        say and I'm happy to have it. It resides in my daughter's room now as she often listens to cassettes and
        mentioned that she would like a boombox.</p>

      <p><a href="https://mstdn.social/@neongod/111776689144734175">Here is a video of it in
          operation.</a></p>

      <p>Advert:
        <p />
        <img src="../images/collection/brgmk27_4.jpg">]]></description>
    </item>
    <item>
        <title>Amiga CD32 - Console review</title>
        <link>https://neongod.neocities.org/articles/cd32-console-review.html</link>
        <guid>https://neongod.neocities.org/articles/cd32-console-review.html</guid>
        <pubDate>Thu, 05 Dec 2024 13:12:30 GMT</pubDate>
        <description><![CDATA[    <div class="right-column column">
        <p><img src="../images/cd32-boot.gif"></p>

        <p>The world's first 32Bit console. Well, technically Fujitsu released FM Towns Marty in Japan a few months earlier, but it had a 16Bit bus, so we could still give that credit to the CD32. The console looks surprisingly cheap, but also with some nice touches. It has a mixture of thoughtfullness and cheap costs savings. It was born in the last period of Commodore, thrown together in a desparate attempt as the company was trying to make money from the gaming market. Objectively speaking, the console itself is not a beauty, though to my biased eyes it looks pleasing.</p>

        <p><img src="../images/cd32.gif"></p>

        <p>Commodore's engineers were certainly tasked with putting together a console from existing parts as quickly as possible. So the CD32 is technically an Amiga 1200 with the addition of a CD drive. It's been stripped of all the excess stuff, but they've left the option to expand it, so you can add a module to make it a full-fledged Amiga, and even an MPEG1 accelerator module (FMV) to watch VideoCDs.</p>

        <p>The designers have also thought about making it easier to port games developed from other platforms, so the CD32 got a custom chip called Akiko, which controls the CD and can do hardware Chunky2Planar conversion.</p>

        <p>Contrary to popular belief, it has not been spared the ability to save games. It has 1Kb of Flash memory, which can store up to 100 game saves and a highscore list. There is also a graphical interface (localizedl), which can be accessed from the boot screen. You can see a list of the saved games in memory and the software is intelligent enough that when the 100 slots get used up, it will start overwriting the oldest one. You can also lock certain slots so that they are never overwritten. Of course, the games will also speak the language we choose for the system (if they include localisation).</p> 

        <p><img src="../images/cd32-locale.gif"></p>

        <p>The Audio CD player interface is equally excellent. It has a host of options that's on par with a more serious desktop player: shuffle, repeat, adjustable length intro, you can turn tracks on/off one by one and sort the order in which they play. The icing on the cake is that a animation of the CD disc spins when the disc starts spinning and the laser light on screen reads the disc where the real laser is.

        <p><img src="../images/cd32-audiocd.gif"></p>

        <p>There's an RCA audio output for audio and S-Video, TV modulator and composite output for video. 2 joystick or mouse connectors and a keyboard option.In addition, there is of course an headphone jack out with separate volume controls. The CD drive is double speed and the firmware of the microcontroller handles CD-I, MPEG and Photo CDs (rewritable CDs are not handled). The CD reader itself is a Sony KSM-2101BAM, for which Chinon made the circuitry. The CD driver has a standard 18-bit (8x oversampling) DAC which, in addition to providing excellent quality, can mix external sources such as MPEG audio with Amiga audio via the digital audio input on the CD32 expansion connector.</p>

        <p>The power supply connector is round, which differs from the other Amiga's, which are sqare. At first glance this seems a bit stupid, but it's not by accident. On other Amiga power supplies the power button in on the power supply itself, while the CD32 power supply is always in an on state (like the C64's), and the power switch in on the console. If you could use the CD32's power supply with an other Amiga, you could easily damage the machine. The CD32 and the Commodore A590 (hard drive) power supplies are exchangable.</p>

        <p>Why is it still cheap?
        Because there are many little details that show off the cost savings. For example, the joypad connectors have been stripped of their cover plate, so the motherboard connectors are routed directly to the plastic casing, and you can almost "see" inside the machine through the opening above them.</p>

        <p><img src="../images/cd32-ports.gif"></p>

        <p>The volume control for the headphones is a shoddy little plastic stick, it's a miracle it didn't break off immediately and I'm actually surprised that it's still intact on many machines today. The Power and Disk LEDs have been reused from the Amiga 1200 as is, and they are placed in a recessed curved place on the case, while the LED panel is flat, so it doesn't follow the curves of the machine. The power button is coming straight out of the C64 (leftover C64 parts).</p>

        <p><img src="../images/cd32-controls.gif"></p>

        <p>As the Amiga was never really popular in the US, the CD32 was debuted in the UK and later made available in European an other markets, with moderate success. Over 100.000 units were sold. But unfortunately Commodore's debts and lawsuits prevented the company to launch the console in the US market, declaring bankruptcy before it. 

        <p>Unfortunately not many CD32 exclusive titles were released, most of the games are re-releases or enchanced versions of Amiga 1200 (and Amiga 500) games. Amiga owners of the time had little incentive to buy the machine. Despite the console's moderate success at launch, it's very doubtful that it would have remained competitive on the market with the arrival of the Playstation and the Amiga userbase declining due to moving to IBM compatible PC-s, mostly due to it becoming a requirement at school or the desire to play Doom and other 3D games the Amiga was lacking. Nowadays, however, the CD32 is a great option for people who like retro games and want to revisit the Amiga games library. Games on CDs are longer lasting than their floppy counterparts, no need to swap floppies or messing around with installing the game, and as a bonus, most CD32 versions include CD audio music and intro animations.</p>

        <p><img src="../images/cd32-games1.gif"><small>Microcosm, Banshee, Alien Breed 3D</small></p>

        <p><img src="../images/cd32-games2.gif"><small>The Adventures of Flink, Skeleton Krew, Litil Divil</small></p>]]></description>
    </item>
    <item>
        <title>CD32WB - Workbench CD for CD32</title>
        <link>https://neongod.neocities.org/articles/cd32wb.html</link>
        <guid>https://neongod.neocities.org/articles/cd32wb.html</guid>
        <pubDate>Fri, 06 Dec 2024 15:38:42 GMT</pubDate>
        <description><![CDATA[    <div class="right-column column">

        <p>I made a simple Workbench CD for the Amiga CD32, which can be used on an unexpanded machine. It needs no keyboard, can be used with only the joypad via an on screen keyboard. There are many game collection CDs available (some can even be used for listening .mods or watch .anims), but I missed the AmigaOS look'n'feel, so I made a system for myself.</a></p>


        <h3>What can it do?</h3>
        <p>You can listen to .mods, .sids, you can watch Amiga and scene related pictures, anims, try some games and demos, read documents (the complete AmigaDOS manual, the CD32 developer kit and many CD32 related articles from Aminet), you can browse other CDs, listen to audio CDs, and most of all, you can expand it to fit your needs, put your favourite games, demos, on it before you burn the iso, if you want.</p>

        <h3>How to use it?</h3>
        <p>Very simple. just burn the ISO with your favorite CD burner. Be careful to burn it with the slowest possible speed, and use CD-R disks only, the CD32 doesn't support CD-RWs. Put the disk in your CD32 and it will boot. That's all.</p>

        <p>CD32WB will boot to a full featured Workbench environment (MagicWB icons, KingCON, MUI, ToolsDaemon, optional MagicMenu, etc) and will leave 1.5Mb chipmem free. The booting process is optimized, it loads and extracts almost everything to RAM, boots from there, then cleans it up. This way the booting time is 2-3x times faster, and saves the health of your CD drive too. But don't forget, the CD drive in CD32 reads max. at 300Kb/s, so the booting will still take much more time than on hard drive equipped Amiga.</p>

        <p>If you hold down the red button of the joypad during booting, it will enter the 'boot-with-no-startup' mode, and you will get a shell window with an onscreen keyboard and 1.8Mb free chip memory. It's not possible to get more memory on CD32, because the Extended ROM, the joymouse and onscreen keyboard takes up the rest, but it still can be enough to run games and demos that won't run from Workbench. If you type 'menu' or even shorter 'm', you will get a quicklaunch menu. Check the readme on the CD for more shell command aliases.</p>

        <p>Here is how it looks:</p>

        <div class="image-row"><img src="../images/cd32wb1.gif"><img src="../images/cd32wb2.gif"></div>]]></description>
    </item>
    <item>
        <title>Discover new music (without algorithms)</title>
        <link>https://neongod.neocities.org/articles/discover-new-music.html</link>
        <guid>https://neongod.neocities.org/articles/discover-new-music.html</guid>
        <pubDate>Fri, 06 Dec 2024 16:46:30 GMT</pubDate>
        <description><![CDATA[    <div class="right-column column">
      <div class="inline-content">
        <p>The Current mood of the Internet is: <a href="https://www.imood.com/imood"><img
              src="https://moods.imood.com/internet/current.gif" alt="The current mood of the Internet at www.imood.com"
              border="0"></a></p>
      </div>]]></description>
    </item>
    <item>
        <title>Complete Fred Fish Disk Catalog</title>
        <link>https://neongod.neocities.org/articles/fred-fish.html</link>
        <guid>https://neongod.neocities.org/articles/fred-fish.html</guid>
        <pubDate>Fri, 06 Dec 2024 16:39:33 GMT</pubDate>
        <description><![CDATA[    <div class="right-column column">
        <h3>Amiga Library Disks</h3>

        <p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fred_Fish">Fred Fish</a> collected and published a great collection of public domain, freeware and shareware Amiga software between <a href="https://groups.google.com/g/net.micro.amiga/c/NsLSHhHHI_4/m/UsP8Y_ixh4YJ?pli=1">1986</a> and 1994. He made over 1000 disks. It's one of the best resources for older Amigas, like the A500, as most of these programs cannot be found on Aminet or elsewhere. This is the full catalog of the disks, to help with finding what you're looking for.</p>

        <p><h3>Download</h3></p>
        <p>The contents of the disks can be downloaded from <a href="http://ftp.funet.fi/pub/amiga/fish/" target="_blank">ftp.funet.fi</a> (in lha format) or the <a href="https://archive.org/details/commodore-amiga-collections-fred-fish" target="_blank">Internet archive</a>.</p>

        <p><h3>Catalog in text format</h3></p>
        <p><a href="../fredfishcatalog_v2.txt">Contents of the disks</a> (Disk Number: Program | Description), <a href="../fredfishxref.txt">Cross Reference</a> (Program | Version | Disk Number | Author, in alphabetical order), if you're after a particular software, you can see which disk contains it.</p>]]></description>
    </item>
    <item>
        <title>How to play Frontier: Elite II (Amiga version)</title>
        <link>https://neongod.neocities.org/articles/frontier-elite-II.html</link>
        <guid>https://neongod.neocities.org/articles/frontier-elite-II.html</guid>
        <pubDate>Tue, 19 Nov 2024 19:39:04 GMT</pubDate>
        <description><![CDATA[    <div class="right-column column">
      <h2>The procedurally generated galaxy awesomeness</h2>
      <p>What is Frontier: Elite II you ask?</p>

      <p>It's a space trading and combat simulation game developed by David Braben and released in 1993 for the Amiga,
        Atari ST, and MS-DOS. The sequel to the 1984 classic Elite. It's building on the originals open-world gameplay
        with vast improvements in realism, scale, and depth.</p>

      <p>Get lost among millions of stars, planets and moons, with thousands of them to explore. You can hyperjump
        between solar systems, get on orbit around planets, and even enter the atmosphere and land on them. Heck, you
        can even watch the sunset from their surface! Some have settlements, others have underground facilities. Some
        planets have space stations orbiting them where you can dock. All with a relistic space flight and landing
        simulation with Newtonian mechanics.</p>

      <p>You assume the role of a starship captain, free to explore, trade, and engage in combat across the universe.
        You can choose your own career path, from trading and mining to piracy and bounty hunting or joining the
        military and going for some assasination and spying missions. You have complete freedom to choose how you wish
        to progress and there is no narrative or end goal. If not becoming the most powerful and rich star-lord of the
        galaxy, haha.</p>

      <p>Oh, and I forgot the best, the game barely fills one floppy disk (It's 650kb)! Technically it comes on two, but
        the second disk contains only some save states. It's a good idea to make a backup copy and use that for saves
        though. If you have a hard drive, just copy the executable and launch it from Workbench.</p>

      <p>The box contains a registration card, a game manual, a quick-start guide, a <b>gazetter</b> with touristic
        highlights from the universe and <b>stories booklet</b> about life on the frontier, and a <b>map of the
          universe</b>! How cool is that!? It's so huge it hardly fits on my desk!</p>

      <img src="../images/games/frontier-eliteII-0.gif">

      <p>The game runs even on an Amiga 500 with 1Mb of RAM, but as it uses 3D vector graphics, it tends to run slow on
        stock systems and benefits greatly from a faster CPU. It can be painfully slow around large objects, especially
        when landing on planets. You can turn down the level of details and some effects to increase the framerate a
        bit. The game is one of the reasons in itself why many longed for a turbo card or a higher-end Amiga. No
        surprise that the intro sequence was often used as kind of a benchmark of an Amiga's speed.</p>

      <h2>Start the game</h2>

      <p>Insert disk 1 into your Amiga and the game will load. It starts with the intro sequence that you can skip.</p>

      <p>You can now select the point of start among these three options:</p>
      <dl>
        <dt><img src="../images/bullet02.gif"> Ross 154 system, planet Merlin (9.35 light years away from Earth)</dt>
        <dd>The recommended option, as you start with the most well equipped ship</dd>
        <dt><img src="../images/bullet02.gif"> Solar system, planet Mars</dt>
        <dd>If you're homesick, you can start from our solar system, but you get less resources</dd>
        <dt><img src="../images/bullet02.gif"> Lave system, Lave station</dt>
        <dd>You can also start with the Cobra Mk III ship familiar from Elite</dd>
      </dl>

      <p>Or from a saved game.</p>

      <p>Once you made you choice, you land in the game immediately, so let's see how to play. You have your dashboard
        on the bottom of the screen. <b>Actual</b> shows the speed of your ship in the moment, while <b>Set</b> the
        desired speed. It takes time to accelerate and slow down. <b>Alt</b> shows your altitude from the surface of the
        nearest planet, while <b>Relative to</b> is the gravitational pull or the reference of the nearest planet. You
        can see we're on Merlin now. Our status is <b>Landed</b> and we're seeing the <b>Front View</b> of the camera.
      </p>

      <img src="../images/games/frontier-eliteII-1.gif">

      <p>Below <b>Actual</b> on the left there is the <b>Current Date</b> and below them are the <b>Time controls</b>.
        You can speed up time significantly or even pause it completely. You'll have to use it if you want to get
        somewhere in sanity, otherwise travel will take pretty much forever. But be careful, slow the time back if you
        get near your destination or will likely crash and die! If you hyperjump or get attacked, the time will slow
        back to normal automatically.</p>

      <p>You can see the radar screen in the middle which shows other ships nearby (currently none) and the three
        angeled bars one of which is green is your fuel gauge.</p>

      <p>The buttons on the last row are numbered and can be activated by pressing the appropriate Function-key on the
        keyboard too. They can be pressed several times to iterate through several screens. From left to right:</p>
      <p><b>F1</b> - Camera view front, back or outside<br><b>F2</b> - Galaxy or solar system map (see
        later)<br><b>F3</b> - Ship equipment, commander profile and cargo inventory details<br><b>F4</b> - Telephone
        used for many things. Local services like requests, jobs, trading when landed, or calling other ships or a space
        station while in space, asking for a landing permission, a price list or just broadcasting an SOS into the void,
        in the hope someone will receive it<br><b>F5</b> - Radar or Weapon display<br><b>F7</b> - Engine control or
        autopilot (if we have one)<br><b>F9</b> - Landing gear in or out<br><b>F10</b> - Turn planet and object name
        display on or off.</p>

      <p><b>ESC</b> - Settings. You can set the level of detail sounds, music, simulation details here. But also load a
        save game (F7), save the game (F8), delete a save (F9) or exit to the title screen (F10).</p>

      <img src="../images/games/frontier-eliteII-6.gif">

      <h2>Map view</h2>
      <p>Press <b>F2</b> and enter the map view. This view is used to plan your travel between solar systems. You can
        move around with the <b>arrow keys</b> and as you move, different objects will get selected. You can also rotate
        the view in 3D if you hold down the <b>right mouse button</b> while moving the mouse. Pressing the <b>C</b> key
        will set the view back to default.</p>

      <img src="../images/games/frontier-eliteII-4.gif">

      <p>This screen redefines the buttons on the bottom-right side of the screen, so you can do a lot of things here:
      </p>
      <p><b>F6</b> - Information on the currently selected system and it's objects<br><b>F7</b> and <b>F8</b> zoom in
        and out<br><b>F9</b> display details<br><b>F10</b> galaxy view</p>

      <p>When you press F6 and enter the information screen, you can click on planets and moons to reveal information
        about them. An important detail here is if the selected object has any <b>Major starports</b> to land on.</p>

      <img src="../images/games/frontier-eliteII-3.gif">

      <p>Note how the button mapping changed again!</p>
      <p>Pressing <b>F7</b> here will show information about the economy of the system which is crucial to determine
        what to buy and sell in a given system as prices will vary across different regions of the universe. <b>Major
          exports</b> mean you can usually buy those cheaply here and sell them for a better price somewhere where those
        are considered <b>Major imports.</b> Same the opposite way. <b>Illegal goods</b> usually pay well on the black
        market, but you can get caught by the police.</p>
      <p><b>F8</b> is for information on government, allgiance and population. Some systems are part of the Federal
        alliance, which is pretty safe, others are Imperial which can be more dangerous.</p>

      <p><b>F10</b> here does almost the same as pressing <b>F2</b> (or the map button twice on the main screen), even
        their icons are the same. It will bring up the local planet 3D view which you can rotate the same way as the
        other 3D map views and zoom in and out with <b>F7</b> and <b>F8</b>. The only difference I found is that if you
        invoke this screen by pressing F2 (or the map button twice), you can also select destinations. Notice the bottom
        right icon showing a red star. Use this to pick a desination.</p>

      <img src="../images/games/frontier-eliteII-5.gif">

      <p>It will show up on your HUD as green rectangles and aid your navigation or allow the autopilot to be used to
        fly you there. If you zoom onto a planet, you can select a station or settlement you want to land on. If you
        want to trust the autopilot with landing, it's a very good idea to save before you try, as the basic autopilot
        unit has a poor accuracy and sometimes can crash you.</p>

      <h2>Take off</h2>

      <p>But enough of rambling, let's take off! First you need to ask for a flight permission, otherwise launching
        without clearance will cost you a fine. Press the telephone <b>F4</b> and ask for a <b>Launch Request</b>.</p>

      <p>Clearance is granted and you can take off immediately. Press <b>F7</b> to turn on the engine. You're flying!
        Press <b>F9</b> to pull in the landing gear. Hold the right mouse button while moving your mouse and turn your
        ship pointing upwards, then press and hold the <b>Enter</b> key to add throttle. <b>Right Shift</b> is used to
        reduce throttle (even to minus to go in reverse). Pressing the <b>Both mouse buttons</b> or the <b>Space</b> key
        will fire the lasers, which is not a good idea right now near the base, as the defence systems and the police
        will shoot you down for violating the law. Wait with trying it out until you're in a distance.</p>

      <img src="../images/games/frontier-eliteII-anim-1.gif">

      <p>Now press the camera icon <b>F1</b> once to switch to the reverse view and speed up the time a little. Look,
        soon you're leaving the planet!</p>

      <img src="../images/games/frontier-eliteII-9.gif">

      <p>Soon you're out of the atmosphere of Merlin and in outer space. It's maybe a good time to try out the
        hyperspace jump and the autopilot. As you start from Merlin with the Eagle Long Range Fighter, you have both on
        board. You can see that if you press <b>F3</b> for the Equipment screen. This ship is equipped with a <b>Class 1
          Hyperdrive</b>, so it can hyperjump in a max 8 light years radius. On the Map View you can notice a purple
        circle around your location, which indicates your jump distance. Don't forget it's 3D, so rotate the view, some
        targets might be too far above or below.</p>

      <p>There is also a <b>Scanner</b>, which provides the radar view in the bottom middle of the screen, an
        <b>Automatic Pilot</b> and an <b>Atmospheric Shielding</b>, which allows landing on planets. There is also a
        <b>1MW Pulse Laser</b> for close combat and some useful information about Cargo and Cabin space. You have 3
        cargo space remaining, 1 is used as you're carrying 1 ton of hydrogen fuel. You don't have any extra cabins
        though, so you can't transport people or have crew right now. Your cash balance is 100.</p>

      <img src="../images/games/frontier-eliteII-7.gif">

      <p>You can see the cargo you're carrying if you press <b>F3</b> two more times for the Cargo Inventory screen.
        There is a <b>Refuel</b> button here. If you're low on fuel, but have some hydrogen fuel in your cargo space,
        you can refuel by pressing it. Think twice though, as it will refuel even if you still have fuel left in your
        tank and waste your reserves.</p>

      <img src="../images/games/frontier-eliteII-10.gif">

      <p>Press <b>F2</b> for the Map view and use the arrows to scroll and highlight <b>Barnards Star</b>. We're going
        to jump there. Now press <b>F1</b> and notice that there is new button mapped to <b>F8</b> on the bottom right,
        for hyperspace jump. Press it.</p>

      <img src="../images/games/frontier-eliteII-anim-3.gif">

      <p>You're now in the Bernards Star system! If you check the information on this system with <b>F2</b>, then
        <b>F7</b>, you can see that people here seem to like extensive mining and heavy industrial development, they're
        exporting metal stuff like robots and farm machinery, which is a minor import on Ross 154, so we can make some
        money here. Press <b>F6</b> for the information screen of the system to find a starport to land on. There is an
        orbital station called <b>Boston Base</b>, let's go there. You can see that it's orbiting <b>Birminghamworld</b>
      </p>

      <img src="../images/games/frontier-eliteII-11.gif">

      <p>So open up the close system map view with <b>F2</b>, click on Birminghamworld, and zoom in by holding <b>F7</b>
        (takes a while). Press <b>F10</b> to select a target for the autopilot and click on Boston Base. Now go back to
        the cockpit view with <b>F1</b> and turn on the autopilot with pressing <b>F7</b> twice (first will turn on the
        engines, second turn on the autopilot). Now speed up the time.</p>

      <img src="../images/games/frontier-eliteII-anim-2.gif">

      <p>When you get closer, gradually slow down the time acceleration, so the autopilot doesn't accidentally crash you
        into the station. If you're lucky, it will go well and you'll automatically get a docking clearance and the
        autopilot will fly and land you in. You can see a nice animation going through the airlocks and inside the base.
      </p>

      <img src="../images/games/frontier-eliteII-12.gif">

      <h2>Trading</h2>

      <p>The phone screen will automatically come up once you docked. You can ask for a Launch Request and leave the
        station immediately, or explore what this place has to offer. There are lots of things to do. You can visit the
        <b>Shipyard</b> to buy <b>Upgrades</b>, <b>Repair</b> damages, check out the <b>New and reconditioned ships</b>
        or <b>Contact the police</b> to pay any fines. You can also look at the <b>Bulletin Board</b> for any local ads.
        Some people want to work as a crew, others want a taxi. Sometimes there are black market ads for illegal goods
        (especially in more shady places), but you can also go on special missions or join the military. For taking in
        more people you need an Extra Passanger Cabin (in Upgrades) which is over your carrying capacity as it weights 5
        tons or a Cargo Bay Life Support which is 1 ton, but is rather expensive. So let's visit the <b>Stockmarket</b>
        and do some trading first.</p>

      <p>Here you can see all the goods for trade. The Buy/Sell columns have buttons to <b>Buy</b> or <b>Sell</b> that
        particular item. You can also see the price per ton, how much they have in stock and how much of it is in your
        cargo space. Scroll down a bit and Buy one Hydrogen fuel for the jump back to Ross 154, some Farm machinery and
        maybe some Metal Alloys. You're poor and can't afford much unfortunately.</p>

      <img src="../images/games/frontier-eliteII-13.gif">

      <p>Now you can ask for a Launch request and leave the station. An animation will start and soon you're in space.
        You know the drill now. Bring up the map again and move with the arrow keys to select Ross 154. Go back to the
        cockpit view and press <b>F8</b> to jump back to Ross 154. As Sirocco Station on Merlin is the only starport of
        this system, we need to find our way back to there. Bring up the close-up system view by pressing <b>F2</b>
        twice. Click on <b>Aster</b> (the Saturn like planet next to Merlin) and zoom in until you see Merlin. Click on
        Merlin so it gets centered and zoom in until you see the planet in full and Sirocco Station on it appears. You
        might need to rotate it to see it. Press <b>F10</b> and click on Sirocco Station as a target for the autopilot.
      </p>

      <p>Press <b>F1</b>, then <b>F7</b> twice to acticate the autopilot. Speed up the time a bit, until you reach your
        destination. Slow down time when you're near and it's a good idea to save the game now, before attempting the
        landing. Once you landed, you can visit the Stockmarket and sell your goods for some profit.</p>

      <h2>Combat</h2>

      <p>It might happen that you get attacked along the way. A message will appear that your <b>ship is under
          attack!</b> Check the radar screen and try to rotate your ship to quickly find where the attacker is coming
        from and position it in front of you. It can be tricky as he is constantly on the move, but you're moving too!
        It's a good idea to turn off the engine as if you're moving too fast, even if you find the enemy, you'll quickly
        overshoot and lose it again. Don't forget, it's Newtonian physics, you're floating in a direction even without
        applying more thrust. Once you can find the enemy ship, click on it so it gets selected and easier to follow.
        Pay attention to the <b>Distance</b> and weather it's inreasing or decreasing and the rate of it. Add or remove
        throttle with <b>Enter</b> and <b>Right shift</b> to keep it at decreasing at a steady rate and not too fast.
        Once you're closer, shoot with the pulse lasers by pressing <b>Space</b>.

        <img src="../images/games/frontier-eliteII-14.gif">

      <p>If you click anywhere on the radar display with your left mouse button, you enter the weapons screen. If you
        click on the rockets, a rocket will become armed and the button <b>Fire (M)</b> becomes visible. Clicking that
        or pressing the M key would fire a missile to a selected target. You have two missiles so after firing one, you
        need to select the other one if you want to fire again. To unarm a missile click on it again. Click on the black
        area to go back to the radar view.</p>

      <img src="../images/games/frontier-eliteII-2.gif">

      <p>Fire the missiles once you have a good view of the enemy. They can fly for quite a bit, but if you fire from
        far away, there is a bigger chance they get destroyed by ECM anti missile system. Later you can buy such an
        equiment too, which can destroy any mines or missiles within a certain range.</p>

      <p>Winning in combat can be tricky and requires practice. A good responsive mouse can be a big help. It can also
        happen that you get overrun by pirates and the best is to jump away if you can. Don't get discouraged if you get
        killed, you need to get the hang of it. You're on your way to become an Elite pilot!</p>

      <img src="../images/games/frontier-eliteII-15.gif">

      <h2>Mining</h2>
      <p>There are two types of mining in the game. <b>Asteroid</b> and <b>Surface mining</b>. You can fly close to
        asteroids and shoot them, then collect what you find. For this you need to equip your ship with a <b>30MW Mining
          Laser</b>, a <b>Fuel Scoop</b>, and a <b>Cargo Scoop Conversion</b>. It's pretty hard to do though as picking
        up small objects in space is tricky. Surface mining is more straight forward, but still hard as you need to
        learn to land manually (it's easier on objects with lower gravity). You need to find a planet that's rich in
        minerals, is not too hot (below 200 degrees celsius) and preferably not populated if you want to avoid
        attracting attention and land on it. You also need at least 30 tons of cargo space and the <b>MB4 Mining
          Machine</b> equipment. Use the <b>Scanner</b> to test the soil if it's rich in minerals and suitable for
        mining. If it is, click the <b>Mining Rig</b> button on the Weapons screen to place the MB4 on the surface. If
        everything went well, the MB4 will start mining immediately. You can leave and come back later (in about a month
        of in-game time) to collect the produce. The MB4's stores 10 tons of minerals at once.</p>

      <img src="../images/games/frontier-eliteII-16.gif">

      <p>To manage your mining operations and find your equipment again, use <b>F3</b> to get to the <b>Mining Equipment
          List</b> screen. It's a good idea to have them spread around as sometimes other miners or pirates might steal
        your produce.</p>

      <h2>Conclusion</h2>
      <p>This game is huge. In an incredibly tiny package. It improves on it's predecessor in every possible way. The
        area to explore is wast, according to the author even 3 months of continous play wouldn't be enough to explore
        everything. It gives you complete freedom in choosing your play style and is not pushing you towards any
        narrative. It's an immersive experience that can be both relaxing and tense. Overall it's a fantastic sequel to
        a fantastic game, a masterpiece.</p>]]></description>
    </item>
    <item>
        <title>Macintosh Classic II (Performa 200) Restoration</title>
        <link>https://neongod.neocities.org/articles/mac-classic-ii-restoration.html</link>
        <guid>https://neongod.neocities.org/articles/mac-classic-ii-restoration.html</guid>
        <pubDate>Sun, 01 Dec 2024 21:51:06 GMT</pubDate>
        <description><![CDATA[    <div class="right-column column">

        <p>I got a Macintosh Performa 200 for reasonably cheap, but in a pretty poor condition. It was sold as working, but I expected that some recapping work might be needed. Unfortunately when it got to me, it wasn't working any more. Then the seller admitted that it took a few minutes for it to boot after powering it on. From this it was clear that it was already on the verge of dying. It was dirty inside and outside, so it was very much due to give it some love. He offered to either buy it back or pay back half the price, which was a fair deal. I decided to keep and renovate it. </p>

        <p><img src="../images/mac_classic2_0.jpg"></p>

        <p>The first thing I needed was a thin and long screwdriver with a Torx T15 head. I found a cheap kit from <a href="https://www.kjell.com/se/produkter/el-verktyg/verktyg/mejslar-mejselset/dibotech-mejselset-med-30-bits-p40488" target="_blank">Dibotech</a> that has an extender.
        It's needed for accessing the top two screws, that are deep down in the handle cavity of the case.</p> 

        <p><img src="../images/mac_classic2_1.jpg"></p>

        <p>After opening it up, the first thing I did was to turn it on and measure the voltages on the hard drive connector. There should be 5 and 12V there. There wasn't, the analog board was supplying just 9.2 and 3.5V. It was clear that the analog board needed a recap badly.

        <p><img src="../images/mac_classic2_3.jpg"></p>

        Before going any further, I put on some rubber gloves, unplugged the Mac from mains and discharged the CRT with a screwdriver and a cable attached to it and the ground point on the case. Then I gradually disassembled the whole thing. First I removed the logic board, then the analog board, the hard drive and floppy disk bay, the mounting bracket from the front panel and the CRT tube.</p>

        <p><img src="../images/mac_classic2_4.jpg"></p>

        <p>By inspecting the logic board it was clear that the capacitors all leaked, but luckily the battery didn't, and it didn't look as bad as I was afraid it would. I removed the battery and put the board aside. After removing the plastic clips and the paper insulator from the analog board, it looked okay too at the first glance.</p>

        <p>I ordered the recap kits for the logic and analog boards:<br>
          <a href="https://console5.com/store/macintosh-classic-ii-2-smd-tantalum-main-pcb-cap-kit.html" target="_blank">Macintosh Classic II Rev A & B Logic Board recap kit (tantalum)</a><br>
          <a href="https://console5.com/store/macintosh-classic-ii-2-electrolytic-smd-main-pcb-cap-kit.html" target="_blank">Macintosh Classic II Rev A & B Logic Board recap kit (electrolytic)</a><br>
          <a href="https://console5.com/store/catalogsearch/result/?q=macintosh+classic+analog" target="_blank">Macintosh Classic I/II Analog Board  recap kits</a> (check voltage and board revision to match yours)</p>

        <p>Here is a good resource with references and close-ups on what needs to be replaced:<br>
          <a href="https://recapamac.com.au/macintosh-classic-ii-a/" target="_blank">Classic II Logic Board Rev A (4 ROMs version)</a><br>
          <a href="https://recapamac.com.au/macintosh-classic-ii-b/" target="_blank">Classic II Logic Board Rev B (2 ROMs version)</a><br>
          <a href="https://recapamac.com.au/macintosh-classic-analog/" target="_blank">Analog Board (same for Macintosh Classic I and II)</a><br>
          <a href="https://wiki.console5.com/wiki/Macintosh_Classic" target="_blank">Differences between Analog board versions</a></p>

        <p>Schemantics of the Macintosh Classic II (useful for checking continuity between components):</p>
        <p><img src="../images/IMG_9538.WEBP"><img src="../images/IMG_9539.WEBP"><img src="../images/IMG_9540.WEBP"><img src="../images/IMG_9541.WEBP"></p>

        <p>Meanwhile the case could now go to the bathroom for a thorough cleaning. I rubbed it with some dish soap, then let it soak in Vanish, which contains some hydrogen peroxide. After washing it off, it came out pretty nice and clean. There is some yellowing to the case, but it's only apparent at the top where there was a sticker. Overall it doesn't look yellow enough for me to do retrobrighting, maybe in the future. I don't mind keeping my retro gear yellowed to a certain (subjective) level, as it's how they're. I don't expect them to look like brand new. It shows their age and I'm fine with that.</p>

        <p>The next step was to remove the floppy drive from the bracket and give it a good clean. It was completely full of dust! I cleaned it with compressed air, a q-tip and isopropyl alcohol. Gave a gentle clean to the heads and removed the old grease gunk from the moving parts, then applied new grease.</p>

        <p><img src="../images/mac_classic2_6.jpg"></p>


        <p>When the recap kits arrived, I started with the analog board as I wanted to see if the logic board will power up if the analog board provides the right voltages. Recapping the analog board is fairly easy as all the capacitors are thru-hole mounted and there is very good access. There are a lot of caps to be replaced though, so it takes time. After desoldering the first few capacitors, it was obvious how badly they're leaking, I could even tell it from the smell. The board was wet from electrolite under the caps, but lucily it did no corrosion damage yet. I was just in time.</p> 

        <p><img src="../images/mac_classic2_2.jpg"></p>

        <p>After desoldering the caps I cleaned the board several times with IPA and a soft toothbrush. Then I soldered in the new caps and just to be sure, I resoldered some critical connections around the power cable and the high voltage components, where the old solder looked a bit off. Then I put the board back and tried it out.</p>

        <p>The recapped analog board:</p>

        <p><a href="../images/mac_classic2_13_2.jpg"><img src="../images/mac_classic2_13.jpg"></a></p>

        <p>It was providing 5 and 12V correctly now, but the logic board still didn't show any sign of life.</p> 

        <p>Correct voltages:</p>

        <p><img src="../images/mac_classic2_11.jpg"></p>

        <p>So next, recapping the logic board. It's a more delicate task as all the components to be replaced are surface mounted, very small and the space is tight. I wasn't sure how to remove the old caps to reduce the risk of damage. Some suggest using the hot air gun method to avoid the risk of ripping off the pads from the board. I tried the hot air gun method on an another PCB I used as practice, but I found it was hard to control the heat and easy to melt other plastic components or cause burn damage to the board, so I didn't dare to do it on the real one. I decided to go with the pliers method and after using this method for a while on a few boards now, I can recommend it. If done carefully, it's safe and the chance of damaging the pads on the board is minimal.</p> 

        <p>The technique I'm using is to gently wiggle the caps sideways with a plier, then in a rotating motion, just a few degrees. Then I can use my finger to wiggle the cap further until it falls off. Often the cap legs break off and stay on the pads, so they can be safely desoldered or picked up with a desoldering suction tool and/or a wick, and the pads on the board remain intact. I cleaned all the pads this way, then with IPA and inspected the board with a magnifying glass to see if any leads got any damage under the caps, but they all looked fine to me.</p>

        <p><img src="../images/mac_classic2_7.jpg"></p>
        
        <p>So I decided to put on the new caps. I taped the areas off around the caps with a heat resistand tape, as the space can be very tight, especially around the connectors and it's easy to accidentally touch and melt the plastic. I used a thin tip on the soldering iron and 350 degrees Celsius with tradional leaded solder (as it was used on this board originally). I installed quality tantalum caps (with the exception of the 47uF 16V ones), to minimize future leakage.</p>

        <p><img src="../images/mac_classic2_8.jpg"></p>

        <p>After recapping the board, I installed back the ROMs and RAM modules. I took a picture of the board before removing them, as the ROM socket is 2pin wider than the ROMs, so it's easy to mess it up. The order and orientation of the chips also matters of course. The pins towards the expansion port side of the board should be left empty. The notch of the chips should also face this direction. The chip marked with 341-0261 should be the outer one and 341-0257 the inner one. Double check this, as installing them the wrong way will fry the ROMs.</p>

        <p><img src="../images/mac_classic2_ROMS.jpg"></p>

        <p>The recapped logic board:</p>

        <p><a href="../images/mac_classic2_12_2.jpg"><img src="../images/mac_classic2_12.jpg"></a></p>

        <p>I installed a new battery (LS1420 3.6V Lithium) and turned the Mac on. Just to see vertical bars and still no chime. I tried it several times, sometimes it was just garbage on screen, no bars.</p>

        <p><img src="../images/mac_classic2_9.jpg"></p>

        <p>I took the logic board out again and started inspecting it with a magnifying glass for any further damages. I found one leg of the chip next to the floppy connector to be loose. I was not sure if I wasn't careful enough with the cleaning or it came off due to some other reason or maybe corrosion, but I soldered it back on. I also gave the board another clean with IPA on both sides, this time soaking the whole thing in IPA, then contact cleaner, then IPA again.</p>

        <p><img src="../images/mac_classic2_5.jpg"></p>

        <p>Still vertical bars. I started suspecting it was either the ROM or the ROM sockets, so I checked the socket continuity with a multimeter and it looked fine. At this point I was stuck. I needed a set of ROM chips or an another logic board to test and cross-check things. I looked around on the local second hand market and found a dead Classic II with the same symptoms for the equivalent of 50 USD. I decided to take a look, as getting another logic board or even the ROM chips from abroad would cost significantly more and with this I could potentially get more spare parts (which as later turned out was not a bad idea). Luckily it turned out to be the Rev B (2 ROM chip) version as well, so I picked it up. I took the ROM chips out and installed them in the recapped board, and voila, it booted up perfectly!</p>

        <p><img src="../images/mac_classic2_10.jpg"></p>

        <p>I used it for a few hours and everything looked okay. Even the floppy drive works. The next day however, when I turned it on, it just showed a question mark and couldn't find the hard drive to boot from. I swapped the disk with the other Classic II, and with that it booted up just fine. I assume the old SCSI hard drive just gave up. I'm afraid the other drive might die too sooner or later, so I'm thinking about either finding a new-old stock SCSI drive or a SCSI emulator (like the BlueSCSI). Or maybe both.</p>

        <p>Now I have a working Macintosh Performa 200 in a very nice condition, hopefully for many years to come!</p>

        <p>I also have a Macintosh Classic II (the one I bought for parts), that could be revived. Which will probably be the next project.</p>]]></description>
    </item>
    <item>
        <title>Macintosh Classic II - Making new system ROMs</title>
        <link>https://neongod.neocities.org/articles/mac-classic-ii-roms.html</link>
        <guid>https://neongod.neocities.org/articles/mac-classic-ii-roms.html</guid>
        <pubDate>Sun, 01 Dec 2024 21:46:10 GMT</pubDate>
        <description><![CDATA[    <div class="right-column column">

        <p>During the <a href="mac-classic-II-restoration.html">restoration of my Performa 200</a>, I ended up getting another Classic II for parts, to be able to isolate the issue I was having. It turned out that the system ROMs were dead in my machine. I could replace the ROMs from the machine I got for parts, but then I started feeling bad about leaving that poor Classic II by itself and wanted to repair it too. I had to find a way to get new system ROMs. Unfortunately it's almost impossible to find vintage Macintosh ROMs for sale, so the only option was to make my own ROMs by programming EPROMs.</p>

        <h2>Classic II ROM</h2>

        <p>The system ROM in the Macintosh Classic II is 512Kb and it's in two 256Kb ICs. A compatible EPROM is the 512Kb AMD 27C400 DIP-40 and we need two of them. I bought mine from this <a href="https://www.ebay.com/itm/284526280037?var=586103610524" target="_blank">eBay seller</a> and I can verify that for me these worked.</p>

        <p>The Vintage Macintosh ROMs can be found on the internet at several places, but the <a href="https://www.jottacloud.com/s/03020ef057cfc30479e8e2d28ecfd2f41cc" target="_blank">Classic II ROM file</a> is 512Kb, so we need to split that into 2x256Kb before burning it. <a href="http://www.synack.net/~bbraun/classic2.html" target="_blank">This website</a> contains some useful information on the Classic II ROMs and it has a small command line program written in C called <a href="http://www.synack.net/~bbraun/macsrc/c2split.c" target="_blank">c2split.c</a>, that can be used to split the ROM file into two. You can easily compile the program and use it from terminal on MacOS or Linux. But if you don't want to, here are the ROM files I splitted:<br>
          <a href="https://www.jottacloud.com/s/0308399192b169645fe87f76f250c1b2688" target="_blank">341-0257-mod.bin</a><br>
          <a href="https://www.jottacloud.com/s/030120e31d3b88b4bc1b53914729ef90ecf" target="_blank">341-0261-mod.bin</a></p>

        <h2>EPROM Programmer</h2>

        <p>Now that we have the ROM files and the EPROM chips, we need a programmer to burn them. There are two EPROM programmers on the market I found people recommending, one is the <a href="https://www.mcumall.com/store/" target="_blank">GQ-4X4</a>, the other is the TL866-II. Unfortunately the TL866-II (white unit) has been discontinued and replaced with the <a href="http://www.xgecu.com/en/" target="_blank">XGecu T48</a> (also called TL866-III). Even if most sellers or auctions claim to sell a TL866-II (or compatible), you'll most likely get a T48 (black unit), which is in many ways better, but in some ways worse, as it's incompatible with the old adapters. All of these EPROM programmers (even the GQ4x4) need an adapter to be able to burn 16-bit 27C400/800/160 EPROMs. The issue with this is that the socket on the T48 is wired slightly differently and it was rotated so it sits the other way around, which makes fitting the adapters made for the TL866-II impossible (you can't close the lever). Most adapters on auction sites were still made for the TL866-II and won't work with the T48.</p>

        <p>Luckily there is now a <a href="https://www.gotek-retro.eu/t48-eprom-adapter/" target="_blank">27C400/C800/C160 adapter for the T48</a> also, made by Gotek-retro. I decided to go with this solution as I'm in the EU and importing the GQ4x4 (and an adapter for it) from Canada seemed significantly more expensive. So I got an XGecu T48 from Amazon and the 27C400 adapter from Gotek-retro.</p>

        <h2>Programming the ROMs</h2>

        <p>Burning the ROMs with the XGecu Pro software is not straight-forward, but not a rocket science either. I never did this before, but after some trial and error, I managed to figure it out. I was using my MacBook, running MacOS Ventura and Windows 10 in Parallels. If you're going to do the same, pay attention to when you connect the adapter to the USB port, Parallels will ask if you want to connect it to MacOS or Windows, choose Windows. You can get the XGecu Pro application from the <a href="http://www.xgecu.com/en/download.html" target="_blank">official site</a>.</p>

        <p>Here is how I did it:</p>

        <p>Insert the adapter into the T48 unit and the 27C400 EPROM into the socket according to the instructions on the board (align the EPROM towards the lever of the T48, with the notch facing the other way, towards the empty pins). Set the EPROM type switch to 27C400/800/160 and the bank switch to 0.</p>

        <p><img src="../images/mac_classic2-rom_2.jpg"></p>

        <p>In the XGecu Pro software select the IC type and set it to <b>AM27C4096 @ DIP40</b>. This is very important. If you set it to 27C400, it won't work.</p>

        <p>Click load in the toolbar and select the ROM file you want to burn. Leave every setting in loading window on default.</p>

        <p>In the Options section of the main window, turn off every option except Verify After (so it will verify the result after the programming is complete). Set the VPP and VDD voltage value according to the specifications of the EPROM you bought (can be found on the manufacturer's website). It will likely be a value between 12.50V and 13.00V for VPP, 6.50V for VDD write and 5.00V for VCC verify. Puls Delay I left on the default 100us.</p>

        <p>Now click on the PROG icon in the toolbar and start the programming. It will take a few minutes, but should result in a "Programming ...Succeeded" message. Replace the EPROM and do the same for the other file. Don't forget to label the EPROMs in a way that covers the UV sensitive opening on them and mark the notch on the label (if it covers it).</p>

        <p><img src="../images/mac_classic2-rom_1.jpg"></p>

        <p>Pay attention to the orientation when inserting the ROMs into the logic board. The socket pin towards the ROM size selector jumper switch should be left empty and the notch on the ROMs should face in that direction too. The ROMs go into the follwing sockets:<br>
          341-0261 -> Socket U23<br>
          341-0257 -> Socket U22</p>

        <p><img src="../images/mac_classic2-rom_3.jpg"></p>

        <p>It was a success, another Classic II saved:</p>

        <p><img src="../images/mac_classic2-rom_4.jpg"></p>]]></description>
    </item>
    <item>
        <title>Mcbazel ODV-GBS-C scan converter and ODV-II Composite/CVBS/S-Video adapter review</title>
        <link>https://neongod.neocities.org/articles/odv-gbs-c.html</link>
        <guid>https://neongod.neocities.org/articles/odv-gbs-c.html</guid>
        <pubDate>Fri, 06 Dec 2024 15:31:12 GMT</pubDate>
        <description><![CDATA[    <div class="right-column column">

      <p>There are several upscalers and adapters on the market that make it possible to connect old computers and video
        game systems to modern TVs. I decided to buy the <a href="https://www.odv-gbsc.com">Mcbazel ODV-GBS-C</a> scan
        converter and upscaler with an <a
          href="https://www.flashbackltd.com/products/odv-ii-component-cvbs-s-video-to-component-converter-for-retro-gaming-console">ODV-II
          Composite adapter</a>. They can be found at several retailers, I decided to go with Amazon Sweden for the
        quick shipping and no import tax. My choice was motivated by the number of features and connectivity options,
        availability and the reasonable cost.</p>

      <p>I have several systems with different outputs, that I wanted to be able to connect to my TV, which happens to
        have only HDMI inputs. I have a Sega MegaDrive and a Nintendo GameCube with HD Retrovision SCART cables, a
        Nintendo Wii with a component cable, a Commodore 64 that has a composite output (or S-Video at best) and a
        Commodore Amiga that outputs RGB via a SCART cable.
        This setup covers all of them.</p>

      <h2>ODV-GBS-C</h2>

      <p>The <a href="https://github.com/ramapcsx2/gbs-control">GBS-Control</a> is an open source project to modify and
        improve the Tvia Trueview5725 based GBS8200 upscaler, which was used in some arcade machines and make it into a
        generic and awesome upscaler for retro gaming.</p>

      <p><img src="../images/odv-gbsc-3.jpg"></p>

      <p>It features:</p>
      <ul>
        <li>very low lag</li>
        <li>sharp and defined upscaling, comparing well to other expensive units</li>
        <li>no synchronization loss switching 240p/480i (output runs independent from input, sync to display never drops
          as opposed to OSSC)</li>
        <li>on demand motion adaptive deinterlacer that engages automatically and only when needed</li>
        <li>works with almost anything: 8 bit consoles, 16/32 bit consoles, 2000s consoles, home computers, etc</li>
        <li>control interface via web browser (creates a WIFI hotspot)</li>
        <li>good color reproduction with auto gain and auto offset for the tripple 8 bit @ 160MHz ADC</li>
        <li>optional bypass capability to, for example, transcode Component to RGB/HV in high quality</li>
        <li>downscaling, to display modern systems on older screens and CRTs (HD to 240p)</li>
      </ul>

      <p>ODV stands for Original Draw Video and it's the branding used by the chinese manufacturer Mcbazel, that made an
        end-user product from the open source project. But of course, you can build your own if you want to. They also
        make a composite adapter with the name ODV-II composite, in the same orange case design, which can be used to
        add the missing composite input option to the GBS-C (or any other upscaler for that matter).</p>

      <p>Let's see what's in the box and set it up:</p>

      <p><img src="../images/odv-gbsc-4.jpg"></p>

      <p>The unit itself looks well built, the plastic is decent quality and they even added rubber feet to both the
        ODV-GBS-C and the ODV-II composite adapter.</p>

      <p><a href="../images/odv-gbsc-2.jpg"><img src="../images/odv-gbsc-2s.jpg"></a></p>

      <p>There is a VGA pass connector and a SCART connector in the front of the unit, with a 3 state selector switch
        that lets you choose the type of the input coming from the SCART connector, between YPBPR/VGA/RGBS, RGBS or
        RGsB. On the left side the component video and audio input RCA jacks, on the right side the DC power and
        micro-USB power connectors can be found. The back side of the unit features a VGA out and a HDMI out port, along
        with a 3.5mm audio out jack. The GBS-C requires more power than what my Samsung TV provides, so it has to be
        powered either by it's own power supply or a USB power supply.</p>

      <p>The setup is very straightforward, just plug in the power, connect the TV to the HDMI port and your equipment
        to any of the inputs. Then turn the unit on. The ODV-GBS-C auto detects the input. It has an LCD screen and some
        control nobs you can play around with. You can fine tune the color saturation with the RGB nobs and move around
        the menu and select (press) with the fourth nob.</p>

      <p>ODV-GBS-C disassembled (Image by MSX.org):</p>
      <p><a href="../images/ODV_GBS-C_PCB.jpg"><img src="../images/ODV_GBS-C_PCBs.jpg"></a></p>


      <p>The menu is simple. It allows you to select an output resolution, load a predefined preset, do a factory
        reset/restart and view the current output settings. The more advanced settings are in the web UI.</p>

      <p>The GBS-C provides a WIFI hotspot where it's configuration interface can be reached. It appears as
        <b>gbscontrol</b> in your network list. The default <b>password is qqqqqqqq</b>. Once you're connected, open a
        browser and a navigate to <b>192.168.4.1</b></p>

      <p>Here you can create, modify and delete presets, align and scale the image to fit (if needed), enable scanline
        emulation and fine tune some more advanced stuff. The UI provides a good explanation of all options if you click
        on the question mark.</p>
      <div class="image-row">
        <a href="../images/odv-gbsc-5.jpg"><img src="../images/odv-gbsc-5s.jpg"></a><a
          href="../images/odv-gbsc-6.jpg"><img src="../images/odv-gbsc-6s.jpg"></a><a
          href="../images/odv-gbsc-7.jpg"><img src="../images/odv-gbsc-7s.jpg"></a>
      </div>]]></description>
    </item>
    <item>
        <title>The case for cassette tapes</title>
        <link>https://neongod.neocities.org/articles/the-case-for-cassette-tapes.html</link>
        <guid>https://neongod.neocities.org/articles/the-case-for-cassette-tapes.html</guid>
        <pubDate>Wed, 20 Nov 2024 14:45:09 GMT</pubDate>
        <description><![CDATA[    <div class="right-column column">
      <p>I like to listen to music in an old fashioned, analog way. I grew up among vinyl records and cassette tapes.
        Vinyl was already fading out, while cassettes were the now. I listened to my parents' tapes a million times and
        made my own mix tapes. I waited for the billboard charts and request-a-song programs on the radio and recoded my
        favourites. I also bought a fair share of original tapes from Virgin Megastore. I had my own tape recorder and a
        walkman I used to take to school and listen to music on the way or during school breaks.</p>
      <p>Years later when CDs became popular, I had a collection of CDs too and I burned many of my own CDs, but
        cassettes always had a special place in my heart.</p>
      <p>After many years of listening only digitally, first MP3s on a computer, later on iPod, then on streaming
        services, I realized how much it affected the way I listened to and discovered music. Digital music formats made
        skipping songs increadibly effortless, which discourages listening to whole albums. You kind of pick your
        favouries and skip the rest. I noticed doing that already with CDs, but not with cassettes, where forwarding and
        rewinding took time and a lot of battery (if on the go). I knew by heart which track will come next and I
        noticed that I had a special connection to those albums I listened on cassettes.</p>
      <p>But streaming had an even bigger impact on my listening habits, making it a much less focused and conscious
        experience. I just picked an artist I liked and let the algorithm do the rest. It's a great way of of
        discovering new music you could say. But for me, it wasn't. Music became part of the background noice. I got
        trapped in one (or a few) genres and I couldn't remember almost any of the artists I was listening to. My
        playlists and library were full of songs I liked at some point in time, but almost all of them were from
        different artists I knew nothing about.</p>
      <p>I realized this when my son asked what is my favourite band and the only ones that came into my mind were the
        ones I listed to way before I started using streaming. Whose albums I bought and listened many times. The ones I
        held in my hand while I listened, staring at the cover art and reading every single line of lyrics, or the bios
        of the artists.</p>
      <p>Discovering music was a completely different experience too. It was more of a conscious activity. Both a
        personal and a social one. I read magazines, album reviews, picked them up on the radio, went to stores and
        listened to the ones I think I might like there. But I also got tips and albums from friends. All this have been
        replaced by automation, making it effortless, but also impersonal and not conscious.</p>
      <p>The more choice and selection we have, the less the choice means, and it applies to everything, not only music.
        If you have 1000 video games on your shelf you can pick from, none of them will become really special to you.
        Sonic the hedgehog 2 is my all time favourite platform game. Why? Because besides it's an absolute masterpiece,
        it was my only game cartridge on my Mega Drive for months, before I could afford buying something else. I played
        it through countless times. I knew every level by heart. I think the same applies to music, and if you want to
        get that magic back, and increase the quality of your music listening experience, you need to take the control
        back, make it more conscious and limit your access and selection artificially.</p>

      <img src="../images/collection/technicsrsd200.jpg">

      <p>This realization lead me to the decision to buy a tape deck and a Walkman once again. An advantage of tapes
        compared to vinyl is that there are a wide variety of players of all sizes. But even good quality tape decks can
        fit into tight spaces, while vinyl players often need a clearance above them for the lid to open. This was a
        limiting factor for me when deciding on an analog music solution as I had only a shelf under the TV for it in
        our living room furniture. Another advantage of tapes is their small size. They require less space to store and
        they allow music to be portable. They also have a decent sound quality (depending on the type and quality of the
        tape and the players) and a signiture sound.</p>

      <p>I chose a used Technics RS-D200 tape deck with two heads, Dolby B, instant recording and manual tape selection.
        It's still in a very good condition and pretty affordable too.</p>
      <p>I was also very happy that I found an unused Walkman WM-EX-162 for a bargain. I had the same model as a child.
        It doesn't have radio built in, but there is MegaBass, type selection (normal and CrO2/Metal), AVLS (Automatic
        Volume Limiter System) to protect your ears and it's pretty economical with batteries. Still as new. Perfect for
        listening to tapes while working or taking a walk.</p>

      <img src="../images/collection/walkmanwmex162.jpg">

      <p>I still had some old tapes in a shoebox that I can listen to again now. I made some mix tapes from the stuff I
        really liked recently and I also found and bought several new releases. I started reading music magazines and
        album reviews again, <a href="http://www.treblezine.com" target="_blank">Trebelzine</a> is my current favourite.
        I started looking at new cassette releases on <a
          href="https://bandcamp.com/?g=all&s=new&p=0&gn=0&f=cassette&w=0" target="_blank">Bandcamp</a> and other places
        too. An often overlooked advantage of cassettes is that it allows independent artists to self-release their work
        in a physical format. Bandcamp is usually my first choice, as if you buy a physical release from them, you
        usually get the lossless digital version as well, which is not the case if you buy a physical release from
        Amazon or other retailers.</p>

      <p>One of my biggest musical discoveries last year was Low. I'm so glad I found them! The more I listen, the more
        I love their albums. They play a minimalistic slowcore indie rock and with amazing vocal harmonies. It's so sad
        that there won't be more with Mimi's mesmerizing voice. I have the last three Low albums so far, Hey What
        (2021), Double Negative (2018) and Ones and Sixes (2015).</p>

      <p>Another one is Weyes Blood. Natalie Laura Mering has been performing under this stage name since 2003 and
        developed a unique sound of melancolic chamber pop-rock. I think she is way underrated. I have her latest two
        albums so far, and Titanic Rising (2019), And in the Darkness, Hearts Aglow (2022) are both among my most
        listened albums currently.</p>

      <img src="../images/collection/low.jpg"><img src="../images/collection/weyesblood.jpg">]]></description>
    </item>
</channel>
</rss>
